<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A covert from the storm, or, The fearful encouraged in times of suffering from Rev. 2. 10 : fear none of those things which thou shalt suffer ... / by Nathanael Vincent ...</title>
            <author>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64957</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V404</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6000</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12379418</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12379418</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60678</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64957)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60678)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 649:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A covert from the storm, or, The fearful encouraged in times of suffering from Rev. 2. 10 : fear none of those things which thou shalt suffer ... / by Nathanael Vincent ...</title>
                  <author>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 142 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation II, 10 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Faith.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60678:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60678:1"/>
            <p>A COVERT FROM THE STORM.</p>
            <p>OR, The Fearful encouraged in Times of SUFFERING: FROM</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rev. 2. 10.</bibl> 
               <hi>Fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt ſuffer; behold the Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon, that ye may be tryed, &amp; ye ſhall have tribulation ten dayes; be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee a Crown of life.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Nathanael Vincent,</hi> a Preacher and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner of Jeſus Chriſt, and written during his cloſe confinement, when few could come at him but his God, who yet abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly made up the want of other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60678:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60678:2"/>
            <head>To <hi>Him</hi> that is Higher than the <hi>Higheſt,</hi> and will ſhortly come to <hi>judge</hi> the world in <hi>righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Mighty Lord!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>A <hi>Priſoner approaches to thy footſtool, and not without ſome confidence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed not for evil doing but for well doing. That which men account his crime, thou haſt made his duty, and by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this he hath incurred their diſpleaſure; but he hopes he hath avoyded thine. He was willing to caſt the Net over a great many, that the more might be taken, and by being taken, ſet indeed at liberty. He was deſirous that the Subjects of thy Kingdome might be multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therefore he ſpake to ſuch great multitudes, and he verily thinks however men may cenſure it, thou doſt not call it Raſhneſs, or Zeal not according to knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Since thou haſt commanded thy Meſſengers</hi> to go into the High-wayes, and as many as they find to bid to the Marriage: <hi>Since thou layeſt an injunction upon them,</hi> to preach the Goſpel to every creature, <hi>ſurely thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>r didſt intend</hi> their compaſſion and care
<pb facs="tcp:60678:3"/> ſhould be confined to a very few: <hi>Oh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that every</hi> Five <hi>of them that hear thy voyce and follow thee might be increaſed</hi> unto ſo many thouſands! <hi>Thin Congregations are a lamentable ſight:</hi> Let them therefore fly as a Cloud, and as Doves to their windows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Incline the hearts of Magiſtrates to pity and moderation; let their Sword be drawn only againſt thoſe that are Malefactors truly ſo called, not againſt ſuch as would fain be at work for thee, and turning many unto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs: Convince them that 'twill be the deſign and deſire of a godly Miniſtry, to make their Hearers better Subjects to their earthly Rulers, as well as to the King of Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy Priſoner who is in this</hi> Gate-houſe <hi>during thy will and pleaſure, earneſtly Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for his liberty. He deſerves to be laid aſide, but deſires to be uſed: he would fain have the Priſon Dore open to let</hi> him out, <hi>but is a great deal more earneſt to have the Pulpit dore open to let</hi> him in, <hi>that he might again be preaching of thy Goſpel. He longs to be warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſecure, who ſee not the Sword drawn out againſt them; to be ſtopping the madmen who are making ſuch haſt to eternal deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; to be inviting the miſerable to mercy, &amp; the loſt unto a Saviour.</hi> Where is thy zeal &amp; thy ſtrength, O Lord, and the ſounding of thy
<pb facs="tcp:60678:3"/> Bowels, and thy mercies! are they reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed? <hi>Oh pity immortal Souls that are going to Hell by Droves; and in ſome places, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours are ſo far from hindring, that being exemplary for looſneſs and impiety, they go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them to perdition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy Priſoner bleſſes thee that ever he had the honour to be in bonds for thee. The worſe of thee, even thy Croſs is not at all to be diſlik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The enlargments of his heart have been greater, then when he was at liberty; his peace hath been more perfect: Thy preſence is ſo ſweet, that he would go to any place to have more of it. Thou haſt given in that grace which is glory begun: he confidently believes this Gaol will make him more meet for the glorious liberty of thy Children; and that he ſhall praiſe thee for ever for what he hath endured.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy Servant can ſay it with boldneſs before thee, that he honours the Authority thou haſt ſet over him;</hi> he hath put others in mind to be ſubject to Principalities and Powers, to be ready to every good work; <hi>and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers it is his own duty to be thus ſubject. Only he hath preached contrary to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates Command, becauſe thy Command is ſo expreſs for preaching; and thou preſſeſt it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Paſtours, as</hi> they love thee to feed thy Lambs, to feed thy Sheep.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60678:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh thou dreadful and heart-ſearching Judge! cauſe the integrity of thy Noneon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Servants to ſhine ſo bright, as to break through all unreaſonable prejudices!</hi> Let their righteouſneſs be brought forth as the Light, and their judgment as the Noon day; <hi>that that ſeverity may be at length aſhamed of it ſelf that's uſed towards them. Oh haſten haſten thy ſecond appearing, that the ſecrets of hearts may be diſcovered, and that it may be made manifeſt before men and Angels, who have worſhiped thee the righteſt way; who moſt have ſought thee, and leaſt themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy Servant being taken off from preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was willing to be ſome way beneficial to thy Church; therefore his Pen hath been going when his tongue could not. And if ſouls are edified and encouraged, if thy Kingdome and Name and Glory be any way by this Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting advanced, then the higheſt end will be attained, which is aimed at by him, who is not, who would not be his own, but by milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Obligations is engaged to be</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine Eternally, Nathanael Vincent.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60678:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READERS, Eſpecially thoſe that were wont to be his Hearers.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Readers:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>NEed Arguments be uſed with the toſs't in a tempeſt to put into an Haven? or with the purſued by the avenger to fly to a Sanctuary? Their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is the beſt Rhetorick to perſwade them to that which is for their own ſecurity. And if your danger were more deeply and rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, you would haſten to the Lord, whoſe Name is a ſtrong Tower, and who hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be</hi> an hiding place from the wind, a covert from the Tempeſt, as Rivers of water in a dry place, and as the ſhadow of a great Rock in a weary Land, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Devil hath great wrath becauſe he knows he hath but a ſhort time: We in this latter age of the World muſt expect more furious aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults from him, becauſe the day of Judgment, unto which he is reſerved, is haſtning. His in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments are enraged, and drive on furiouſly. But what is all their force and power, to the
<pb facs="tcp:60678:5"/> ſtrength of that Almighty Lord, who if you leave to him, and truſt in him, hath covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to uphold you? How inconſiderable is their anger, when your believing thoughts have dwelt a little upon his kindneſs and compaſſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be not affrighted at the Croſs of Chriſt, 'twill, when felt and ſweetned, be found no more a burthen to you, than wings are to the Bird flying in the air, or Sails to the Ship cutting through the Sea; 'twill be a means to mend your pace, and make you run ſwifter in your Race, towards the Prize of the high Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of God. If your Lord had not known the eaſineſs and uſefulneſs of his yoak, he would never have required you to have taken it upon you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have Preached much to your incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Now I am taken off, a ſad ſilence is impoſed on me: Only my mouth is ſtill open to the Lord for you, that you may ſtand perfect and</hi> compleat in all the will of God. <hi>I could not have ſatisfied either you or my ſelf, unleſs in this my reſtraint and retirement, I had written ſomthing that might be a furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to your faith &amp; joy in this hour of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation. The bleſſing of the Father of Spirits go along with this Book! Oh that believers
<pb facs="tcp:60678:5"/> may be ſtrengthened and refreſhed by it! And if enemies read it with an ill mind, the Author wiſheth that by reading it their minds may be changed, and for their own ſakes as well as his made better.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Nathanael Vincent.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:60678:6"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Before you read I pray correct theſe faults, elſe the ſenſe will be quite ſpoyled in ſome places.</p>
            <p>PAge 37. Line 12. for <hi>confeſs</hi> read <hi>profeſs.</hi> Page 43. line 14. for <hi>preſervation</hi> read <hi>preſervative.</hi> Page 47. line 18. for doth <hi>uphold</hi> read <hi>do uphold.</hi> Page 53. line 15. for <hi>offences</hi> read <hi>offenders.</hi> Line 16. of the ſame page for <hi>heartily</hi> read <hi>preſently.</hi> Line 17. for <hi>very</hi> read <hi>many.</hi> Line 18. for <hi>even</hi> read <hi>ſeven.</hi> Page 77. line 10. for <hi>Goal houſe</hi> read <hi>Gatehouſe.</hi> Page 88. line 9. for <hi>ever</hi> read <hi>even.</hi> Page 100. line 21. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Page 104. line 23. for <hi>religious enemies</hi> read <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Religion.</hi> Page 107. line 3. for <hi>expreſſive</hi> read <hi>expreſs.</hi> Page 108. 116. for <hi>ſhal</hi> read <hi>ſhould.</hi> Page 109. line 1. for <hi>their</hi> read <hi>this.</hi> Page 113. line 3. for <hi>loved</hi> read <hi>beſtomed.</hi> Page 119. line 12. blot out <hi>upon you.</hi> Page 120. line 5. for <hi>but</hi> read <hi>beſt.</hi> Page 121. line 27. for <hi>fear of God is ſeen</hi> read <hi>face of God is ſeen.</hi> Page 123. line 27. for <hi>communion</hi> read <hi>coniunction.</hi> Page 124 line 6. for <hi>fall</hi> read <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</hi> Line 16. of the ſame Page, for <hi>fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> read <hi>killed.</hi> Page 125. line 8. for <hi>unſpeakable</hi> read <hi>uncapable.</hi> Line 22. of the ſame Page, for <hi>attended</hi> read <hi>attained.</hi> Line 24. for <hi>mouths are ſongs</hi> read <hi>mouths are full of ſongs.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:60678:6"/>
            <head>A COVERT FROM THE STORM.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Rev. 2. 10.</bibl>
               <q>Fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt ſuffer: Behold the Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon that ye may be tryed, and ye ſhall have tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation ten dayes: be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee a Crown of life.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>A Light is hung up at the porch of this Book, which is ſo very myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious: the three firſt Chapters are more eaſy to be underſtood than thoſe that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60678:7"/> follow: Here the waters of the Sanctuary are but up to the head, but preſently they grow ſo deep, as that the talleſt muſt be fain to ſwim. I am perſwaded that one reaſon why the Holy Ghoſt ſpeakes ſo ſublimely, is, that man when he reads may ſometimes lay aſide the book, and cry, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, O the depth! and being the more humbly ſenſible of his own ignorance and weakneſſes, may pray with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er earneſtneſs, that the Spirit who was the <hi>Inſpirer</hi> would alſo be the <hi>Interpreter</hi> of the Revelation.</p>
            <p>Seven Epiſtles, or Letters, dated from Heaven, indited by the Son of God, are ſent to the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia:</hi> He who knew their works, owns what is right, taxes what was a miſs, and calls to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and amendmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and charges them to hold faſt thoſe good things which they had received, as being a treaſure highly worth the keeping. The Captain of their ſalvation encourages to quit themſelves like men, that overcoming they might in the end be crown'd.</p>
            <p>The Text I have choſen lyes in the Epiſtle ſent to the Church in <hi>Smyrna.</hi> Poor they were in the World, and yet rich to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God; and it is not unlikely that for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60678:7"/> the ſecuring of their ſpiritual riches, as to worldly things they had been impoveriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Chriſt knew their works, and as their works, ſo likewiſe their tribulation; he knew alſo how to ſupport them under the heavieſt and moſt preſſing burthens, nay, to render all their troubles advantagious, by conducing to their more perfect purity and peace; and therefore bids them in no wiſe to be afraid, <hi>Fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt ſuffer,</hi> &amp;c. Our Lord came to deliver, not only from the ſting of Death, and from the curſe of the Croſs and affliction, but from the fear of both.</p>
            <p>The words may be analyſed or reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into three parts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Here's a general encouragment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all kinds of ſuffering. <hi>Fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt ſuffer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Among other ſufferings im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment is ſpecified and foretold, where take notice 1. who is the procuring cauſe of impriſonment, and he is the <hi>Devil.</hi> 2. The perſons impriſoned, <hi>Some of you.</hi> All the Saints ſhall not be in bonds toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 3. The end of their impriſonment, which their God aims at in permitting it; 'tis <hi>that they may be tryed.</hi> 4. Although they have tribulation it ſhall not be long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liv'd,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60678:8"/> 
               <hi>it ſhall laſt but ten dayes,</hi> that is a very ſhort ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We have a ſtrict charge given, <hi>Be thou faithful,</hi> and that even to <hi>the death:</hi> Perſeverance muſt run parallel with our lives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> A ſure and glorious promiſe, perſwading to this faithfulneſs and endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the end; <hi>I will give thee a Crown of life.</hi> Here's a <hi>Crown,</hi> a word that carries great dignity and advancement: This <hi>Crown is a Crown of life,</hi> or, a <hi>living Crown.</hi> The Garland that's put upon the heads of triumphant Saints will never wither, their Crown will never fade, there will be no death to throw it off again when once they have received it. This Crown ſhall be given; to ſhew that what they do, or can do, bears no proportion to ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: Neither their active nor paſſive obedience is meritorious. Grace, Grace, muſt be written round the Crown of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, becauſe freely beſtowed. <hi>I will give</hi> this Crown ſayes Chriſt: I who have purchaſed it by my death, who have it in my keeping, who am the Lord of glory, and alive for evermore.</p>
            <p>The text is very fruitful, and affords ſeveral very excellent and uſeful points of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60678:8"/> Doctrine. I ſhall raiſe theſe nine, which flow naturally from the words, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon them all.</p>
            <p>The firſt Doctrine is this, <hi>He that will be a Saint, ſhall be a ſufferer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond this, <hi>No ſufferings ſhould cauſe the Saints to be afraid,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third this, <hi>Among other troubles, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me Believers endure bonds and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Fourth this, <hi>The Devil is the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoner of Believers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Fifth this, <hi>That Saints are impriſoned, that they may be tryed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sixth this, <hi>The Tribulation of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers will not laſt alwayes, after ten dayes, that is a ſhort time, a period will be put to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Seventh Doctrine is this, <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſufferings a Chriſtian is expoſed to, he muſt be faithful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Eighth this, <hi>A Chriſtians faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs muſt run parallel with his life, to the very death he muſt be ſtedfaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ninth and laſt is this, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon thoſe who continue faithful to the death, Chriſt will certainly beſtow a Crown of life and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="doctrine">
               <head>The Firſt Doctrine:</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He that will be a Saint ſhall be a ſufferer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60678:9"/>
               <p>The Spirit ſpeaks hardly any thing more expreſſely then he doth this truth. The Apoſtle tells what afflictions and perſecutions he met with, and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torilvaffirms, that none ſhall eſcape. Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution they ſhall meet with, if not in one kind, in another. Drops ſhall fall upon every Saint, though ſome may be wet with greater ſhowers, 2 Tim. 3. 10, 11, 12. <hi>But thou haſt fully known my Doctrine, manner of life, purpoſe, faith, long-ſuffering, charity, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, perſecutions, afflictions, which came unto me at</hi> Antioch, <hi>at</hi> Janium, <hi>at</hi> Lyſtra, <hi>what perſecutions I endured there: But out of them all the Lord delivered me: yea and all that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus ſhall ſuffer perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Conſult alſo, Act. 14. 22. <hi>Confirming the ſouls of the Diſciples, and exhorting them to continue in the faith, and we muſt through much tribulation enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> The journies end is glorious, but the way is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ough that leads to it, it lies through many tribulations. Self-denial and the Croſs are doctrines which Chriſt preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all his followers, Luk. 9. 23. <hi>And he ſaid unto them all, if any man will come after me, let him deny himſelf, and take up his croſs and follow me.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:60678:9"/>
               <p>Two things are here to be inquired in to. One is, <hi>whence the ſufferings of the Saints ariſe?</hi> The other, <hi>What is the reaſon of this diſpenſation?</hi> Or, <hi>Why the Lord ſuffers thoſe he loves, to be thus exerciſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Whence the ſufferings of the Saints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe?</hi> They are both <hi>from the god of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> world,</hi> and <hi>from the world it ſelf.</hi> Earth and Hell do both combine to trouble the heirs of Heaven, as they are going to their inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance.</p>
               <p>1. The Saints ſufferings ariſe <hi>from the god of this world:</hi> So Satan in Scripture is called. He commands the generality of the world, who are at his ſervice, and are lead by him at his pleaſure: and thoſe whom he cannot rule, he is reſolved, what he can, to moleſt and diſquiet. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil began betimes; righteous <hi>Abel</hi> did feel the effects of his enmity and hatred; and he continues this perſecuting Trade unto this very hour. And till the whole Body of Chriſt be taken up where the Head is, Satan will be as a thorn, to pierce and trouble them.</p>
               <p>It will not be amiſs to examine the matter further; and to ſearch into the cauſe, why Satan thus endeavours to load the Saints with ſufferings.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Devil bears an implacable hatred to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60678:10"/> the Saints Head, the Lord Jeſus.</hi> He would fain have killed Chriſt from the birth; and incited <hi>Hered, to make ſuch weeping and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in Rama,</hi> becauſe of the children that were ſo inhumanly butchered, <hi>Mat. 2. Our Lord was tempted by the Devil,</hi> Mat. 4. who would gladly have foiled the Second, as he had done the Firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> but he could not prevail. <hi>The Devil is ſaid to have put it into the heart of Judas to betray Chriſt.</hi> All which plainly ſhews his hatred of the Son of God. The works of! Chriſt and of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, are quite contrary. Satans work is to murther and deſtroy; therefore he hath his name <hi>Apollyon,</hi> Rev. 9. 11. But Chriſts work is to ſave. The Son of God was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted to this very end, that he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the works of this Deſtroyer; and the Son of God hath got the Victory, <hi>He hath ſpoyled Principalities and Powers, and made a ſhew of them openly, triumphing over them in his Croſs,</hi> Col. 2. 15. He is now aſcended on high, and is at his Fathers right hand: And the old Dragon being full of wrath, to ſee him ſo exalted, ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s his venom at the Members, which are in his reach, for the Heads ſake. And ſurely our Lord will look upon himſelf as the more obliged to ſtand by his ſuffering ſervants, ſince 'tis for his ſake partly, that this adverſary is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60678:10"/> ſo liberal of his arrowes, and ſhoots ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny at them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Devil is full of envy at Believers themſelves.</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oon as ever he had ſinned; preſently the chains of darkneſs were clapt upon him; he was immediately caſt down to hell, no patience being ſhewn, no pity extended, no means of recovery offer'd, 2 Pet. 2. <hi>God ſpared not the Angels that ſinned, but caſt them down to Hell, and delivered them into chains and darkneſs to be reſerved unto judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> But believers, though by nature the children of wrath and diſobedience, are pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, pardoned, adopted, ſaved: A Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is provided, and that Remedy made effectual, through the application of it, to their recovery, and the recovery of their loſt bleſſedneſs. Now this fills Satan with envy, which is both his ſin and torture, and envy ſtirs him up to do what miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief he is able.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Devil diſlikes holineſs where-ever he finds it.</hi> He hates indeed all the children of men; but thoſe that are ſanctified and renewed, in a ſpecial manner. As he is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtitute of, ſo he utterly dereſts and abhors the image of God, which ſhews the fearful depravation of his nature. 'Tis no wonder he runs to the utmoſt length of his chain to harm the Saints, <hi>who have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60678:11"/> put off the old, and put on the new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſs and true holineſs,</hi> Eph. 4. 24. Sin is arrived at its full growth, 'tis come to its perfection in the Devil. Holineſs he ſtrikes at, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to diſcourage and hinder where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he finds it. Thoſe who reſemble Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan in this, the meaſure of their iniquity is fuller than they are aware of.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The Devil deſigns by the perſecuting of the Saints, to promote his intereſt and Kingdom.</hi> This Prince of darkneſs is a very proud ſpirit, he would, by his good will, have the whole world his ſlaves and vaſſals. How does he rage, when any of them, whom he lead captive, are reſcued from him! He is ſedulous to eſtabliſh his Throne and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality. Oh that Saints were as zealous and diligent to advance the honour and intereſt of the King of Saints! The Devil hopes to promote his Kingdom, not only by flattering ſinners into his ſubjection, but alſo by affrighting them from the ſervice of another Lord.</p>
               <p>There are theſe five wayes whereby Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan is like to be advantaged in times of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He is likely to get advantage, <hi>by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the weak in faith.</hi> He hopes that they who have but weak hands, and feeble
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60678:11"/> knees, will not eaſily get over thoſe ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocks, which in times of trouble are caſt in their way. And if their hearts do faint and fail, not only they themſelves, but Religion looſes ground; and what ground is loſt, the Devil gaine. He ſet upon <hi>Peter</hi> when he was weak; and how far did he prevail? <hi>Peter</hi> falls moſt ſhamefully, and his fall coſt him dear; and how was the prejudice againſt Chriſt in the High-Prieſts Hall encreaſed, when one of his followers, thus with curſing and ſwearing, did ſo ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deny him? Satan deſires to have weak Saints eſpecially, that he <hi>may ſift them as wheat:</hi> 'Tis well our Lord prayes for them, <hi>that their faith may not fail</hi> in the hour of temptation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Satan is likely to get advantage, <hi>by making the Temporaries fall away.</hi> He know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that the Sun of perſecution ſhining <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot, will ſcorch the Seed that's ſown, and ſprings up in ſtony ground, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 21. Temporary believers are quickly offended at Chriſt, and become unbelievers again. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a ſtorm ariſes, they will leave the Ship where Chriſt is, and loving carnal caſe, and an whole skin, will put in to the next harbour. Let Chriſt be alone, if he will, in a tempeſt, they will not then accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany him. And when many of theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60678:12"/> Diſciples do forſake the Lord, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal hearts are more confirmed and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt him; as if 'twere unſafe, and conſequently a very unwiſe part to be of the number of his followers. The going away of temporary believers, is very like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to hinder others from engaging to ſuch a Maſter who is ſo much deſerted.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Satan is likely to get advantage in the times of ſuffering, <hi>by ſtaving off them that are without, from coming in, and cloſing with Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> When any begin to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think themſelves, to conſider their wayes, and to mind ſalvation, the Devil, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the day of calamity, fills their minds with ſuch ſuggeſtions as theſe: That the Croſs of Chriſt is heavy; that 'tis dreadful to be hated of all men; that tribulation will pinch their fleſh; that name, relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, credit, eſtate, nay and perhaps life may be called for, as ſoon as ever Chriſt is cloſed with. And hereby he ſtrangely and ſtrongly prevails upon timerous and corrupted nature. <hi>You had better,</hi> ſayes Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, <hi>underſtand when you are well, and keep your ſelves ſo; you had better live in peace and plenty, as the moſt of thoſe about you do, than be ſingular in your way, and by that ſingularity make ſo many enemies, and pull down upon your heads ſo many troubles.</hi> And truly the fleſh hath an open
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60678:12"/> ear to ſuch counſel, though it be very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and pernicious.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Satan is likely to get advantage in the time of ſufferings, <hi>By leſſening the Saints number.</hi> He cares not how many of theſe are cut off; he delights in the high and crying ſin of thoſe who be the Saints De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers; and he knows that when belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are cut off, though he cannot trouble <hi>them,</hi> they cannot trouble <hi>him</hi> any longer, by undermining of his Kingdom, as before they did. Saints, whoſe faith, and love, and hope, ſet them above the fear of ſufferings, are perſons whom the Devil fears, as well as hates; therefore he wiſhes he were well rid of them: theſe will hearten and <hi>ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then their brethren</hi> to ſtand faſt in the Lord; theſe conſequently are the marks at which he aims, and would fain quite run them down to the very grave by tribulation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Satan is likely to get advantage in the time of ſuffering, <hi>by hindring the preaching and progreſs of the Goſpel.</hi> Where perſecution is vehement, Viſion grows rare; in thoſe places where the joyful ſound, the glad tydings of peace, uſed to be heard, there is a ſad ſilence. The Prophets are driven in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to corners, and not ſuffered to cry aloud to ſinners to awaken them, <hi>and turn them from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60678:13"/> Satan unto God.</hi> And when faithful La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers are thrown aſide, Satan expects a plentiful harveſt.</p>
               <p>Thus the Devil aims at the promoting of his Kingdom, by ſtriking at the Saints: But the Lord commonly at laſt out-ſhoots him in his own bow, and makes theſe ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings tend to the ſufferers good, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpels glory and encreaſe. God can a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh his ends by means that ſeem contrary; he can make Satan and perſecutors ſerve his Son by enlarging of his Borders, which they thought and hoped to have narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. He can <hi>thruſt forth</hi> (ſo the word in the original <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies) Labourers into his Harveſt again. And though men and Devils ſtand to hinder their entrance and working, if the Lord <hi>thruſt them in,</hi> in they ſhall go, and work with more power and ſucceſs then ever.</p>
               <p>2. The Saints ſufferings ariſe, as from the god of this world, <hi>ſo from the world it ſelf.</hi> What Chriſt ſaid concerning the Jewes who went about to kill him, may be applied to thoſe who are the troublers of his Members, <hi>They are of their father the Devil, and the luſts of their father they will do,</hi> John 8. 44. He is a <hi>Lyar and a Murtherer,</hi> and ſo are they. They firſt raiſe lyes of Believers, confidently affirming them to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60678:13"/> be rebellious, ſeditious enemies to King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes (though indeed the Pillars of the Nations where they live) and having ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt them, they endeavour their ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine; having miſrepreſented them, they fall upon them: They lye in ſaying, the Saints are not fit to live, and then they ſtrive to root them out of the Land of the living. Thus they make nothing of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing at once both the ſixth and the ninth Commandment.</p>
               <p>Now the reaſon which moves the men of this world to trouble the Saints of God is four<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>old.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Saints are not of the world.</hi> Our Lord ſpeaks thus to his Diſciples, <hi>Joh. 15. 19. If ye were of the world, the world would love his own, but becauſe ye are not of the world, but I have choſen you out of the world, therefore the world hateth you.</hi> Again, he ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>John 17. 14. I have given them thy word, and the world hath hated them,</hi> the reaſon is, <hi>becauſe they are not of the world, even as I am not of the world.</hi> Believers are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the men of the world, and this <hi>unlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> is the ground of <hi>diſlike.</hi> They dare not be careleſs of their ſouls, fearleſs of God, prodigal of the day of Grace, as the world are. <hi>They are not conformed to this world, but transformed by the renewing of their minds, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60678:14"/> they prove what is the good, the acceptable and perfect will of God,</hi> Rom. 12. 2. And truly the world is a great enemy to all them that are <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> to its manners, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though its manners are ſo exceeding vain and ſinful.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Saints are of God.</hi> And the men of the world, who are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if they hate the Saints likewiſe.—<hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam for a ſaevit in umbram.</hi> Some Beaſts have ſuch an antipathy to man, that they will run at his Picture where they ſee it. In like manner, the world cannot endure thoſe who have the image of God reſplendent and ſhining in them. <hi>Abel was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oted becauſe his works were righteous,</hi> 1 John 3. 12. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digiouſly ſtrange! that believers ſhould be abhorr'd, becauſe beautified with grace, and be hated becauſe lovely.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Saints are a conviction to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the ungodly.</hi> 'Tis ſaid that <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rod feared John the Baptiſt, becauſe he was a juſt man and holy. Herods</hi> conſcience was ſtruck with an aw, by the majeſty and beauty that appeared in the converſation of that burning and ſhining light. The holineſs of <hi>John</hi> made <hi>Herods</hi> wickedneſs the more apparent; and at laſt he makes an end of him who did ſo much diſturb him in his filthy and unlawful pleaſures. Wicked
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60678:14"/> mens conſciences do, not unuſually, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach them, becauſe they are ſo unlike believers. <hi>Do you not ſee,</hi> ſayes conſcience to them, <hi>how watchful the Saints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> leſt they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>r into temptation? Do you not ſee how they pray, how they ſtrive, and how they live? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly you are in danger of the ſame Hell, which they endeavour to avoid; and capable of the ſame Kingdome, which they uſe ſuch violence to take:</hi> And by ſuch language as this their falſe peace is intrencht upon; they cannot ſin with ſuch freedome and delight, but the ſecret and condemning whiſpers of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſowr and leſſen their pleaſures: and this exceedingly raiſes their choler; and like ſo many wolves they fall upon the harmleſs ſheep of Chriſt which live among them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The Saints act contrary to the perverſe wills and inclinations of wicked ones.</hi> They make conſcience of obeying that injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 1 <hi>Pet. 4. 2. That he no longer live the reſt of his time in the fleſh, to the luſts of men, but to the will of God.</hi> They are taught not to follow a multitude; and to judg that way unſafe and leading to ruine, which is the broadeſt, and moſt crowded with paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. They dare not run with others to all exceſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iot, and upon this ſcore they are ſpoken evil of. Two things make the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60678:15"/> Saints to be maligned by the men of the world; <hi>The Saints hate what the men of the world love,</hi> and <hi>vilifie what the men of the worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> adore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>They hate what the men of the world love<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Believers hatred of ſin is univerſal, they ſtrike at ſin in themſelves and others; they cannot<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with patience ſee ſuch a curſed thing ſerved by ſo many; they teſtifie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> its evil and deſtructive nature, and hereby though undeſervedly, contract the ill wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of them who prefer their ſins before their ſouls, and will by no means let their luſts go, though theſe luſts of theirs are ſuch ſure hinderances to their eternal happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Saints vilifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> what the men of the World adore.</hi> As the <hi>Epheſians</hi> of old ſtood up for their Goddeſs <hi>Diana,</hi> ſo the worldly minded cry out, <hi>Great is the Mammon of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs.</hi> But believers trample upon this idolized clay, they call it as it is, <hi>Vanity and vexation of ſpirit,</hi> and are not afraid to let the earthly minded know, that it had been better for them never to have com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into the world at all, than to have nothing but the things of the world to be their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>You ſee now whence the ſufferings of the Saints ariſe, from the world, and from the god of the World.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60678:15"/>
               <p>In the ſecond place we are to enquire, wherefore it is that God permits the Saints who are ſo dear to him, to be thus exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ſufferings.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Saints are exerciſed with ſufferings, that pride may be hid from them.</hi> The ſin of pride cleaves cloſe, ſtands ſtiffly, is not eaſily pull'd down. A mighty hand is fain to be laid upon us, to keep our ſpirits low; and that mighty hand of God is a good hand, when, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>we humble our ſelves under it.</hi> Sufferings make us often to reflect on ſin, and to be the more affected at our guilt and vileneſs. Our weakneſs <hi>then</hi> likewiſe becomes more apparent; we ſee how aſſuredly we ſhould ſink, if an arm from Heaven were not ſtretched forth to ſuſtain us. And when we ſee our vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and our weakneſs, we ſhall not think our ſelves too good to ſuffer, we ſhall not through the haughtineſs of our hearts, fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and be impatient under our loads; thus to do, is unreaſonable, becauſe infinitely more than we feel hath been deſerved; and the way to force the Lord to withdraw, whoſe preſence is our ſtaffe and comfort Sufferings being ſanctified, are hugely ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacious to our humiliation: bearing the yoke will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame our ſpirits, <hi>and make us to put our mouthes in the duſt, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo be there may be h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe,</hi> La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. 29.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60678:16"/>2. Saints are exerciſed with ſufferings, <hi>that they may be proved.</hi> Their faith, and love, and other graces, which are much more precious than gold that periſheth, are tryed by the fire of afflictions, and abiding the fire, will be found unto praiſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory, at the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 7. 'Tis a ſign their grace is ſincere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> indeed, if they follow the Lamb, though he leads them through fire and water; their faith is ſtrong, or elſe it would fail; their love is ardent, elſe it would cool; they are the Lord Chriſts, not only by profeſſion, but by a real incorporation and ſpiritual union, elſe tribulation would cauſe a ſeparation. The Accuſer of the brethren ſayes perhaps to the Lord concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning believers, <hi>Let men but touch what they have, let them be but expoſed to ſuffering for thee, and they will preſently d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ny thee.</hi> But when they prove ſtedfaſt as a Rock in the midſt of the moſt boyſterous waves; when they will part with any thing rather than their integrity, their ſincerity is hereby tryed and made manifeſt, and Satans accuſation is evidently proved to be a falſe one.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Saints are exerciſed with ſufferings, <hi>in order to their refining.</hi> Though they are not reprobate ſilver, yet much droſs not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding is mixed with the right met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60678:16"/> hence it follows that the furnace of tribulation is but needful. How do belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers beſtir themſelvs to keep in with God, when the world frowns, and threatens and ſtrikes at them? Oh then the folly of backſliding is very viſible; how do they cry to have all thoſe wide breaches that ſin hath made, cloſed and made up again! how do their ſpirits make a diligent ſearch after every thing that defiles, and which may prove a dark and uncomfortable cloud between the Lord and them: No luſt but they are more than ordinary ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to have it ſlain: And they profeſs perſecution will be eſteem'd a priviledge, if it conduce to more perfect purity; and that they will kiſs the rod that drives ſin and folly far away from them. As the promiſes of ſupport, ſo the promiſes of fanctification are often pleaded, wherein, God engages <hi>to cleanſe them from all their filthineſs, to ſave them from all their unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, to give them his ſpirit, and to cauſe them to walk in his ſtatutes, and to obſerve his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and do them,</hi> Ezek. 36. 25, 26. The Saints in diſtreſs do hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſs, and the Lord doth by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees ſatisfie that hunger: And the more they are freed from ſin, their ſufferings are the ſweeter.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:60678:17"/>4. Saints are exerciſed with ſufferings, <hi>that they may be weaned from things viſible.</hi> Troubles are as ſo much gall put upon the worlds breaſts to wean us from it. In time of tribulation the Lord, not only by his word, but by his Providence, ſpeaks to us after this manner; <hi>Ariſe, this is not your reſt, build not your neſt here, the whole Forreſt is ſold to Death, and every Tree muſt ſhortly down.</hi> 'Tis in the time of peace uſually that the world inſinuates it ſelf; in trouble its em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptineſs is more eaſily diſcerned. As <hi>belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are crucifyed to the world, ſo the world is crucifyed unto them,</hi> Gal. 6. 14. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the world as that which ſin hath brought a curſe upon, and therefore to be watch't againſt, leſt it prove a ſnare; and then they look upon the world with ſuch a kind of eye as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did upon Chriſt in his exinanition, <hi>Iſa. 53. They ſee no form nor comlineſs in it, that they ſhould deſire it.</hi> Believers in the evil day, beſide their hard uſage from the world, which makes them leſs to like it, have more affecting thoughts of eternity and the world to come: and hereupon the things which are temporal grow contemptible, and are not counted worth a look, 2 Cor. 4. 18. <hi>Whilſt we look not at the thnigs which are ſeen, but at the things that are not ſeen;</hi> and not without reaſon,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60678:17"/> 
                  <hi>for the things that are ſeen are temporal, but the things that are not ſeen are eternal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Saints are exerciſed with ſufferings, <hi>that they may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ted for, and long for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance that is above.</hi> By ſufferings they are made conformable to their Head, and are perfected and ripened more and more for glory. Therefore afflictions are ſaid <hi>to work for us a weight of glory.</hi> Glory is promiſed to the ſufferer for righteouſneſs ſake; and <hi>'tis a righteous thing with God, to give reſt to them who upon ſuch an account are troubled,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 1. 7. By trouble they are made meet for reſt; and the greater the tribulation, the glory 'tis likely will be the greater, to be ſure the more wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</p>
               <p>When we look round about us, and ſee nothing but matter of grief and ſorrow, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>will make us look upward to thoſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions on high, and long to be there, where ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſuffering will come to a perpetual end. In Heaven there will be an eternal calmneſs and ſerenity; no ſons of violence will be there to diſturb the Saints in their praiſes; no enemies will be permitted to roar in that Congregation; no fear of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or any other puniſhment will be there; but their joy will be like a full Sea, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60678:18"/> not ebb any more for ever: I am now come to the Application.</p>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>USE I.</head>
                  <p>If he that will be a Saint ſhall be a Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer, learn from hence, <hi>They are far from being Saints, who reſolve to give out when once it comes to ſuffering.</hi> Thoſe are not worthy the name of Diſciples, who like the Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, will tarry with Chriſt all the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, but when the cold and ſtormy Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter approaches, do uſe their wings and leave him. Our Lord ſayes, <hi>He that loves Father or Mother, or life it ſelf, more than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, is not worthy of me:</hi> that is, he is not fit to make one of my followers. If trouble make you to be offended, and go away from Chriſt, 'tis a ſign you prefer eaſe and peace and proſperity before him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently that you have not the faith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned of Gods Elect. If you did <hi>indeed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, Chriſt would be precious,</hi> and that even then, when he is a ſtone of ſtumbling, and a rock of offence to others, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 7. If you did indeed believe, you would be of the Apoſtles mind, who counted all things but dung, when compared with Chriſt; and eſteeming them but dung, no wonder
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60678:18"/> if he contentedly ſuffered the loſs of them, that his intereſt in his Lord might be ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Phil. 3. 8. For whom I have ſuffered the loſſe of all things, and do count them but dung that I may win Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <head>USE II.</head>
                  <p>If he that will be a Saint ſhall be a ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, <hi>then 'tis but reaſonable for every Saint to expect ſuffering.</hi> Reckon upon it that troubles will be met with in your way to Heaven; none ever arrived to that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>fair Haven,</hi> without being toſs't by ſome tempeſts. He that goes to ſea, is not ſo fooliſh as to think it will be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual calm all his Voyage. He that Liſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> himſelf a Souldier, expects ſomtime or other to be engaged. So a Chriſtian ſhould ſit down, <hi>and count the coſt,</hi> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke 14. before he embarque with Chriſt, before he liſt himſelf under this Captain of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And certainly 'twill coſt ſome trouble to be Chriſts follower; none ever faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſerved him, but his fleſh ſmarted for it; though it muſt alſo be affirmed, that this ſmart of the outward, is uſually ſweetned with a far greater pleaſure in the inner man. Our Lord ſpeaks to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60678:19"/> plainly, and without a Parable, <hi>Joh. 16. ult. In the world ye ſhall have tribulation;</hi> but that their hearts might not be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, he tells them firſt, <hi>In me ye ſhall have peace:</hi> And he adds ſecondly, <hi>Be of good chear, I have overcome the world.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="application">
                  <head>USE III.</head>
                  <p>If he that will be a Saint ſhall be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer, <hi>then 'tis the Saints wiſdome to prepare for ſufferings.</hi> Evil dayes will come; but God hath prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ded armour of proof, which if you put on, you ſhall be able to withſtand in the evil day, and having done all to ſtand. I might here enlarge in going over the Chriſtians Armour: but I ſhall only ſingle out ſome pieces, which you muſt not fail to get and uſe in a day of ſuffering, and which, if uſed skilfully, no force, either of evil men, or evil Angels, ſhall prevail againſt you. Though no part of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of God be needleſs, yet eſpecially you muſt take</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Shield of Faith.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Breaſt-plate of Love.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Helmet of Hope.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And cry by Prayer for continual help and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port from above.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:60678:19"/>1, That you may be arm'd againſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, <hi>take unto you the ſhield of Faith.</hi> Yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are in a Battel, Men and Devils thruſting ſore at you that you may fall; What ſhift can you make without a Shield? The Shield is Armour to the other Armour. If Faith be ſtrong, your other Graces will have the greater vigour, and ſtand you in the greater ſtead. Faith will make you victorious. <hi>This is the victory,</hi> ſayes the Apoſtle, <hi>that overcometh the world, even our Faith,</hi> 1 John 5. 4. And it may truly be ſaid, This is alſo the victory that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the god of this world, even our faith; faith prevails againſt both.</p>
                  <p>By faith the Worthies of old of whom the world was unworthy, went through all their tryals, and yet theſe tryals were very ſore: <hi>They were cruelly mocked and ſcourged, they were ſtoned, they were ſawn aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, were tempted, were ſtain with the ſword, they wandred about in ſheep-skins and goat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skins, being deſtitute, afflicted, tormented,</hi> Heb. 11. 37. 'Tis remarkable, that the Holy Ghoſt in deſcribing their puniſhments, ſiath <hi>they were tempted.</hi> 'Tis likely fair means were uſed as well as foul, promiſes of preferment, as well as threatnings of torment, to draw them away from their
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60678:20"/> integrity; and this was a ſore temptation. But faith kept them ſtedfaſt, and rendred the temptation ineffectual.</p>
                  <p>Faith looks to its <hi>Author and Finiſher</hi> the Lord Jeſus, and ſees the world vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by him, and the Principalities and Powers of darkneſs ſpoyled by him; and therefore concludes it will not be long ere more than a conqueſt through him that hath loved the believer will be obtained. And in the mean while Faith relyes upon the word of promiſe, and ſtayes the ſoul on the Lord Jehovah: whereupon the ſoul is both ſupported by an everlaſting arm, and alſo kept in perfect peace, <hi>Iſa. 26. 3, 4. Thou wilt keep him in perfect peace, whoſe mind is ſtayed on thee, becauſe he truſteth in thee. Truſt ye in the Lord for ever, for in the Lord Jehovah is everlaſting ſtrength.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. That you may be armed againſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, <hi>get on the Breaſt-plate of love.</hi> If you love much, you will conſent, when called, to ſuffer much, and not think much of what you ſuffer. If your love to the Lord Jeſus be, as it ought to be, tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and flaming, <hi>many waters will not have power to quench it, all the floods that lift up their waves will not be able to drown it,</hi> Cant. 8. 7.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:60678:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et your love to Chriſt be ſurely groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed. Be well acquainted with your loſt eſtate, your abſolute need of this Saviour, without whom no ſhift can be made, but wrath and ruine are unavoidable. Be well acquainted with Chriſts matchleſs excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, and how he is admirably, and every way ſuited to your deſires and neceſſities, being a Prophet to inſtruct and reduce the ignorant and erring ſoul, a Prieſt to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile his Father to the guilty, a King to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>end from all ſorts, even the worſt of enemies. And as he is <hi>able,</hi> ſo likewiſe <hi>ready</hi> to do all this, and that for <hi>any</hi> who deſire that all this may be done for them. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>deed he rejects thoſe who like only his <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> but count his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> an hard word, his commands grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous; but he never denyed his benefits to any that were willing to have them <hi>all without exception,</hi> purity as well as pardon and peace, grace as well as glory.</p>
                  <p>Our Lord is not unwilling you ſhould, take a v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ew of him. He does not deſire to be loved, unleſs, your eyes being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, you ſee ſufficient reaſon. Sin is loved upon a miſtake; and 'tis upon a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake that Chriſt is deſpiſed. If ſin were underſtood, it would be abhorr'd: and if
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60678:21"/> Chriſts worth were but weigh'd and righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly judg'd of, as he deſerves to be, ſo he would be actually the <hi>Deſire of all Nations,</hi> as the Prophet calls him, <hi>Hag.</hi> 2. 7. Know him therefore, and let your love ſpring from a right underſtanding of him, and then nothing will be eſteemed too good or dear to caſt away, that you may hold him faſt. The worlds ſtore is nothing comparable to the benefits, which he hath purchaſed with the price of his blood. And the moſt ſevere Lawes and Edicts of men, the greateſt torments that they can invent or inflict, are nothing near ſo dreadful as that <hi>Anathema Maranatha,</hi> which is thundred out againſt <hi>any man that loves not the Lord Jeſus,</hi> 1 Cor. 16. 22. <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema Maranatha,</hi> ſignifies, <hi>Let him be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carſed till the Lord comes.</hi> They that love not Chriſt, will have a curſe ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng upon them that never ſhall be removed, and that's infinitely worſe than any preſent ſufferings.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That you may be armed againſt ſufferings, <hi>Let not the Helmet of hope be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Your heads may be lifted up with boldneſs when you have this Helmet on. A lively hope will have a great influence to keep your hearts from ſinking into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60678:21"/> 
                     <hi>Hope is ſtiled the anchor of the ſoul both ſure and ſtedfaſt, and entring within the vail,</hi> Heb. 6. 19. In the ſtorm of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble believers ſhould caſt anchor, and their anchour muſt be caſt upward; there's the Rock of Ages, and in him their anchor is to be faſtned. The Ship ſails not while the anchor is caſt. But a Chriſtian differs, his anchor is faſtned, and yet he ſails at the ſame time; which ſhewes that he ſails moſt ſafely in the midſt of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt fluctuations, towards the Harbour of peace. Let Hope be ſtrong. Hope of a happy concluſion will make preſent affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction be endured with patience.</p>
                  <p>It is the buſineſs of Hope to wait for and expect the accompliſhment of the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>Fides,</hi> ſayes <hi>Luther, intuetur verbum rei, Spes rem verbi.</hi> And ſince the ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which Hope expects, is ſo certain, ſo juſt at the door, and ſo exceeding glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, hardſhip and labour in the way to ſuch a reſt, may the better be diſpenſed with. When the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh through weakneſs complains, and is ready to fail, then Hope encourages the heart, and ſayes, <hi>Yet a little while, and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y;</hi> I expect him, and deliverance and a reward with him, and this expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60678:22"/> of <hi>Hope will never make aſhamed,</hi> Rom. 5. 5. This Helmet of Hope is of ſingular uſe, it covers the head of a Chriſtian, in the day of Battel, it wards off the blows of diſcouragement, which would ſtrike the Head under water. For this reaſon the Apoſtle is ſo earneſt, that the believing <hi>Romanes, might be made to abound in hope, through the power of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Rom. 15. 13.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That you may be armed againſt ſuffering, <hi>cry by prayer for continual help and ſupport from above.</hi> Though you are never ſo compleatly armed, yet there is need of prayer, to call in freſh and renewed auxili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary force from heaven: Therefore the Apoſtle adds, <hi>Praying alwayes with all prayer and ſupplication in the Spirit, and watching thereunto with all perſeverance,</hi> Eph. 6. 18. When men and Devils are wreſtling with you, do you wreſtle with God; and if you can but imitate your father <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and as <hi>Princes prevail with God;</hi> if you have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with the Almighty, who then can be too ſtrong, too hard for you?</p>
                  <p>Fill your mouths with arguments, and cry unto the Lord, <hi>That ſince he hath lead you into the field, he would not leave you in the battel; that ſince trouble i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> near, he would not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60678:22"/> be far <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ff, but near to help you; that ſince 'tis for his ſake you are perſecuted, by his power of Providence you may be preſerved, and your trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles turned to his honour and your advantage.</hi> Tell him, <hi>that your enemies are his, and 'tis becauſe you dare not diſpleaſe him, that men are enraged againſt you.</hi> Tell him, <hi>'Tis time for him to work, for men have made voyd his Law.</hi> Tell him, <hi>that you look and long for his ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that you will never ceaſe your importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, till he appear and own that truth and cauſe which men endeavour to bear down, but you are ſtanding up for unto the Death.</hi> Prayer hath a mighty p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>evalency: <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, there was a kind of omnipotency therein. This weapon hath made <hi>the Church terrible as an Army with Banners.</hi> Perſecutors and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils likewiſe, have many times by Prayer been worſted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="application">
                  <head>USE IV.</head>
                  <p>If he that will be a Saint ſhall be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer, <hi>Let me exhort and perſwade you that are Saints, to bear ſufferings as become you.</hi> Let not fretting, or fear, or ſorrow prevail, unto your diſcompoſure; but manifeſt to all the world, that you have ſomthing of God in you, by undergoing what bare nature
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60678:23"/> would ſink under. Suffer not as wilful, but as conſcientious; be able to give Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture reaſons for what you practice, and for what you refuſe. Beg of the Lord to make your way plain; and the way of duty being diſcovered, though there be a Lion, or a thorn hedge in that way, go forward notwithſtanding.</p>
                  <p>And among others, let theſe encouraging arguments be pondered by you.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>God is glorified by your ſufferings:</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, <hi>on your adverſaries part he is evil ſpoken of, but on your part he is glorified.</hi> 'Tis a ſign you really believe the Lords greatneſs and power, when you had rather have the whole world your enemies, than him to be your enemy. 'Tis a ſign you indeed believe his goodneſs and his promiſes, when you had rather part with all viſible comforts, than be caſt away from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and favour. And by thus believing you glorifie him exceedingly. It argues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that the Lord hath your hearts in good earneſt, when no troubles, no afflictions, which for his ſake you are aſſaulted with, can alienate your affections from him. Further, you proclaim to all, what a good Maſter you ſerve, when your adverſaries by all that they can do, are not able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60678:23"/> you from following him, cannot compel you to forſake his ſervice. And who knows what convictions in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of them that obſerve you, may be the effect of your conſtancy? Who knows but that by this means, ſome may be brought to make tryal of your Lord, and ſo to the liking and loving of him?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>By your ſuffering the Goſpel is advanced.</hi> The mighty power and efficacy of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is ſhewn forth, when it makes and keeps the Diſciples hearts undaunted, though ſufferings in the moſt fearful ſhapes and forms are objected to their view. How is the Goſpel magnified, when believers are content to be the mark for an adulterous generation to ſhoot at, rather than be aſhamed of it? 'Tis evident, that the Goſpel is from God, elſe it could not thus ſupport and comfort. The Apoſtle tells the <hi>Philippians,</hi> Chap. 1. 12. that his bonds and confinement, were to the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpels furtherance</hi> and enlargment; his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren grew bold to ſpeak the word with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fear, and the word ſpoken was the more readily entertained, being credited by ſuſtaining <hi>Paul</hi> and other Saints in all their tribulation.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>By your ſufferings your ſelves are dignified.</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:60678:24"/> You are highly graced, when called forth to be the Lords Witneſſes; <hi>The Spirit of Glory, and of God reſteth upon you.</hi> The Lord ſingles you out to combate with the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of earth and darkneſs, and he will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage, and help, and give you victory. The Apoſtles, when they were beaten, did not murmur, <hi>but rejoiced that they were coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for the name of Jeſus,</hi> Acts 5. 41. Shame is dignity, reproach is glory, loſs is gain, ſorrow is joy, pain is pleaſure, when endured for the ſake of Chriſt. Several of the Martyrs in the <hi>Marian</hi> Perſecution, when they went to the Stake, gave thanks upon this very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that they died a death ſo noble as to dye Martyrs for the truth againſt <hi>Babels</hi> abominations, and to aſcend, as it were, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n fiery Charots to the New <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>When you are ſuffering, what a ſtock of prayers is going for you.</hi> 'Tis an happineſs to be hardly dealt with, ſo we are prayed harder for. Our tribulation makes the bowels of mercy which are in our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to year<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> towards us; <hi>they are bound with us in the ſame Bonds,</hi> and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mpathize in our ſufferings; this makes them the more inſtant and earneſt with the Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies on our behalf. When <hi>James</hi> the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60678:24"/> of <hi>John</hi> had loſt his life, being killed by the Sword; and <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er</hi> had loſt his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, being apprehended and put in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, 'tis ſaid <hi>that Prayer was made without ceaſing of the Church to God for him,</hi> Acts 12. 5. And Prayer having entered into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, brought an Angel to his reſcue, it ſhook the chains off <hi>Peters</hi> hands, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed an iron gate of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s own accord to open to him. Behold the ſtrength of believers prayers!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For my own particular, I ſeriouſly confeſs, that my impriſonment hath moſt happily in this regard befallen me; I have no reaſon to be vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with, but rather to thank my adverſaries for their kindneſſe in thus confining of me. The ſtrictneſſe and cloſeneſſe of my priſon, hath made my caſe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mwhat peculiar; and that alſo is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto good, for hereby the ſpirits of hundreds, both in City and Country, were ſtirred up to pray for me with greater fervency and enlargment: And to have ſo many prayers poured out for One particular perſon, is an ineſtimable priviledge.</hi> My Friends, I thank you, <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d hath anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red your requeſts, I have had that in priſon, which is ten thouſand times better than liberty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> than the world, than life, than ten thouſand worlds and lives.</hi> My Enemies, I cannot but thank you too, <hi>becauſe you were the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60678:25"/> of the mercies I have received; though I really grieve to think that you did me good with ſo much harm to your ſelves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>When you ſuffer, the Lord himſelf ſuffers with you.</hi> Not only your fellow Members, but your Head doth ſympathize and feel your burthens. <hi>In all your afflictions, he is afflicted,</hi> Iſa. 63. 9. You have not an High Prieſt that cannot be touched with the feeling of your infirmities: and the effect of this ſympathie, muſt needs be a moſt tender regard to you, and readineſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you in due ſeaſon. <hi>Luther</hi> very well obſerves, that when any member of the <hi>natural body</hi> is harmed, the ſenſe of pain appears in the head and face, the brows are knit, the forehead wrinkled, and the tongue cryes Oh! the whole countenance is alter'd. And in like manner 'tis in the <hi>myſtical Body,</hi> when any member is wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, if the injurious wretches could but ſee the face of Chriſt the Head, they might plainly perceive he feels the ſtroak, and is wounded in the wounds of his faithful fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers. Therefore when <hi>Paul,</hi> while a zealous ſon of the Jewiſh Church, did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the Diſciples of the Lord, and being exceedingly mad againſt them, did hale men and women, and commit them to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60678:25"/> priſon, Chriſt out of heaven cries out to him, <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou Me?</hi> And ſince the great Phyſitian is himſelf wounded in your wounds, you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently expect an healing balm from him.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. To encourage you, conſider, <hi>Great is the power that reſts upon you in your ſufferings.</hi> Such a power as ſhall not only make you ſtrong as <hi>David,</hi> but as the Angels of the Lord. A Saint ſtrengthned by the hands of the mighty God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> though ſhot at by the Archers, his Bow ſhall abide in ſtrength; therefore in Scripture he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared <hi>to an iron pillar, to a brazen wall, to a defenced City,</hi> Jer. 1. 18. To ſhew, that though he is aſſaulted, and that with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, yet he ſtands firm and unmoved. Little do the ungodly think who is the Saints helper. The Apoſtle conſidering the ſufficiency of that Grace which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in the evil day, profeſſeth he was not ſorry for that dayes approach, nay ſo far from that, he <hi>glories</hi> and <hi>takes pleaſure in it,</hi> 2 Cor. 12. 9, 10. <hi>And he ſaid unto me, my grace is ſufficient for thee, for my ſtrength is made perfect in weakneſs: moſt gladly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will I rather glory in mine infirmities, that the power of Chriſt may<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> reſt upon me. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60678:26"/> I take pleaſure in infirmities, in reproaches, in neceſſities, in perſecutions, in diſtreſſes for Chriſt: for when I am weak, then am I ſtrong.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Great is the peace vouchſafed to ſufferers.</hi> Chriſt ſpeaks of this peace, and having left this Legacy, he adds with reaſon, that they ſhould not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ear or be troubled, Joh. 14. 27. <hi>Peace I leave with you my peace I give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you; not as the world giveth, give I unto you: Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid.</hi> How many doubts and fears have been cured by tribulation? When this for the Goſpels ſake hath been ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to, the heart which before trembled, and was diſconſolate, is filled with joy and peace in believing. And indeed, as trouble <hi>is an evident token of perdition to the troublers,</hi> ſo to them that for well-doing <hi>are troubled, 'tis a token of ſalvation, and that of God,</hi> Phil. 1. 28. Oh the Songs that have been ſung in the night of diſtreſs! Oh the ſweet refreſhing viſits that the Lord of Glory hath given to his priſoners; ſo that thoſe places of confinement, have been ſomtimes turned into the very ſuburbs of the New Jeruſalem. And let not the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſuffering diſmay any; theſe will but occaſion your fuller joy, and more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60678:26"/> conſolation, 2 <hi>Cor. 1. 5. For as the ſufferings of Chriſt abound in us, ſo our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation alſo aboundeth by Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. <hi>If you ſuffer with Chriſt, you ſhall alſo reign with him,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 12. And truly the Croſs is light as a feather, if compared with the Crown. Send forth your <hi>Faith</hi> but as a <hi>Spy</hi> to the heavenly <hi>Canaan;</hi> let it take a view of the Glory there; let it bring but a leaf of the Palms that are to be put into your hands, but a gem of the Crowns that ſhortly will be put upon your heads, and you will preſently be of the Apoſtles judgment, when he ſaid, I <hi>reckon that the ſufferings of this preſent time, are not worthy to be compared to the glory that ſhall be revealed in us,</hi> Rom. 8. 18. Sufferers will find a more abundant entrance into the Kingdome. They are with a great deal of honour pointed at, <hi>Rev. 7. 14. Theſe are they which came out of great tribulation, and have waſhed their Robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.</hi> How many encouragements are here to ſuffer; ſufficient, if duly weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to make you ſuffer, not only with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, but with gladneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="application">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60678:27"/>
                  <head>USE V.</head>
                  <p>I ſhall conclude this Doctrine with a Caution to the unholy: <hi>Do not think your condition happy becauſe freed from ſufferings now.</hi> Your ſin at laſt will find you out; it is purſuing after you to overthrow you, and it will, if you repent not ſpeedily, overtake you. And though you are <hi>not in trouble, like other men, that cleanſe their hearts, and waſh their hands in innocency,</hi> Eternity will be long enough for you to be plagued, and (wo wo to you) then your ſufferings will be extreme, being not at all ſweetned with the leaſt mixture of conſolation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="doctrine">
               <head>The Second Doctrine.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No ſufferings ſhould cauſe the Saints to be afraid.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>Sayes the Text, <hi>Fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt ſuffer.</hi> See alſo Iſa. 37. 3, 4. <hi>Strengthen the weak hands, confirm the feeble knees; ſay to them that are of a fearful heart, be ſtrong, fear not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Two things in the opening of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine are to be done. <hi>One</hi> is to ſhew <hi>that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60678:27"/> there is an aptneſs in the Saints to be afraid of ſufferings. The other</hi> to demonſtrate, <hi>the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonableneſs of giving way to this fear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt place I am to ſhew, that there is an aptneſs in the Saints to give way to fear, when ſufferings are coming: this is implyed in the Text, <hi>Fear not,</hi> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates that by fears they would be aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, though thoſe fears ought to be repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. There is a two fold fear; a fear <hi>that is a duty,</hi> a fear <hi>that is an infirmity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>A fear that is a Duty,</hi> and that is the fear of the Lord: This fear is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of wiſdom, and a great preſervation from evil; this fear is a grace to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, and as a grace is promiſed in the New Covenant. I <hi>will put my fear into their hearts, and they ſhall not depart from me,</hi> Jer. 32. 40. This fear hath nothing of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in it; but as it argues the man bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in whom it hath place, ſo it is very conſiſtent with <hi>delight,</hi> and <hi>great delight,</hi> Pſ. 112. 1. <hi>Bleſſed is every one that feareth the Lord, that delighteth greatly in his Command<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments.</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is fear of God will ſwallow up other fear. If we ſanctifie the Lord of Hoſts in our hearts, by making him our fear and dread, nothing beſides will be ſufficient to diſma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:60678:28"/>2. There is <hi>a fear which is an infirmity,</hi> and that is the fear of man, or any evil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that upon the account of Religion may be brought upon us. This fear in the Text is forbid: Yet this fear is apt to ſeize upon believers; and truly they find it much more difficult to overcome thoſe fears, than the evils themſelves, whereby their fears are raiſed.</p>
               <p>Several things there are, whereby fears are apt to be raiſed in Believers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The greatneſſe of the evils which they may be expoſed to:</hi> Not only their credit, but their livelyhood; not only their lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, but their lives may be ſtruck at. And running the hazard of <hi>loſing all,</hi> makes timorous nature to adviſe, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to diſſwade them from it. Our Lord does not limit his followers to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo far, and no further, but commands expreſsly to ſtick at nothing; the neareſt Relations, the deareſt enjoyments, muſt be hated, when they ſtand in competition with him, that is, leſs loved than he is; <hi>Luke 14. 26. If any man come to me, and hate not his father, and mother, and wife, and children, and brethren, and ſiſters, yea and his own life alſo, he cannot be my Diſciple.</hi> In times of trouble, Men and Devils are let more
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60678:28"/> looſe, and ſo are likely to lay on load on Chriſts Diſciples; and the apprehenſion of ſuch heavy burthens, may cauſe ſome diſmayedneſs of ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Fear is apt to be raiſed <hi>by the proximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and nearneſſe of evils.</hi> When the Saints behold their perſecutors full of fury, their tongues whet like a ſword, and their hands lifted up to give the blow; when they ſee calamity haſtening towards them, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs like an armed man, which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reſiſt nor avoyd, then alſo their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation will be ſtrong to fear.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Theſe evils are heightned by Satan, who endeavours what he can to impreſſe fear upon them.</hi> He repreſents their approaching ſufferings, in the moſt amazing forms, to their imaginations. He tells them, it will be ſad to be the ſcorn of all that look on them, to be counted <hi>the filth of the world, and the off-ſcouring of all things.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tan tells them it will be ſad to have their goods ſpoyled, their houſes taken from them, or leveld with the ground, to ſee their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies undone, and pined with extremity of wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, to feel in their own perſons the hand of violence, eſpecially when ſinful compliance may prevent it. The Devil buzzes in their ears nothing but <hi>Dungeons,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60678:29"/> ſhackles, ſwords, axes, faggots, ſtakes, furious flames,</hi> and thus endeavours to fright them out of the way of righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>And 'tis not unuſual when ſuch dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things are repreſented to their imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to aſſault their faith, and to peſter them with unbelieving and blaſphemous injections againſt Chriſt and his word, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to make them queſtion the certainty and truth of that glorious <hi>life and immortality which is brought to light by the Goſpel,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 10. And if theſe thoughts of infidelity are not watched and prayed againſt, they will dead and overwhelm the heart, and prove of a very ſinking nature. The Lord therefore is to be intreated to rebuke Satan, who by ſuch blaſphemies ſtrikes at his honour, as well as at our ſafety and peace.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Add alſo, <hi>That Grace in believers is imperfect, and therefore fear is the more incident.</hi> There is much of corrupted, as well as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed Nature; and corrupted nature ſides with Satan to affrighten them, that ſo they may caſt faith and a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence over board, to keep the Veſſel from drowning, and ſecure themſelves.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond place I am to ſhew <hi>The unreaſonableneſſe of this fear in the Saint<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:60678:29"/> Now the unreaſonableneſs of it will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly evinced by theſe arguments.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Let us compare the mightieſt enemies of the Saints with him who is their helper.</hi> Their adverſaries may be mighty, but their Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is Almighty. If the everlaſting ſtrength of the Lord Jehovab were but conſidered, fear would be aſhamed of it ſelf in thoſe that belong to him, and are protected by him. Believers enemies (take the very proudeſt and ſtrongeſt of them) in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of God are but <hi>Nothing, leſs than no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and vanity,</hi> Iſa. 40. And is it not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable to be afraid of nothing? and more unreaſonable to be afraid of leſs than nothing? O ye Saints, remember what a power is for you; whoſe hands uphold you, even the very ſame that doth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold all things. Your enemies them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are in Gods hands, <hi>they cannot live or move, or act without him;</hi> they are but wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons in his hand, which cannot ſtrike one blow more than he ſees needful to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you; all the wounds which they make ſhall be healing; and by all their inſtruments of death they ſhall but puſh you forward, and haſten you along in Heavens way.</p>
               <p>And if your mighty God rebuke theſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60678:30"/> perſecutors, preſently they muſt ſtoop and bow, and fall down before him. He can tye their hands, nay take away their breath when he liſteth; and when their breath goeth forth, and they return to their duſt, all their thoughts and deſigns againſt you will periſh, their envy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge will be come to an end, when once the vengeance of God, which is the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of hell fire, hath taken hold of them. The Grave and Hell will keep them far from ever moleſting of you more.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Let a compariſon be made between the cra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tineſſe of believers enemies, and their Gods wiſdome.</hi> The Lord knows the thoughts of man, that they are vanity. He ſees their projects, and knows how to fruſtrate their deſigns. That's a notable place, <hi>Job 5. 12, 13. He diſappointeth the devices of the crafty, ſo that their hands cannot perform their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe; he taketh the wiſe in their own craftineſs, and the counſel of the froward is carryed head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long.</hi> The Lord is wiſe enough, not only to deliver us, but alſo to take the Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in their own craftineſs. He looks and laughs at the plots of <hi>Rome</hi> and Hell to undermine his Kingdom; and that which they intend as a ſupport to the principality of darkneſs, ſhall prove its downfall; and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60678:30"/> 
                  <hi>Sion</hi> ſhall be built on <hi>Babylons</hi> ruines. <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſayes, <hi>there is no wiſdome, nor underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor counſel againſt the Lord,</hi> Prov. 21. 30. And by very good conſequence, there is no wiſdom, nor underſtanding, nor coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel againſt his people; why then ſhould his people fear? <hi>If one wiſe man were able to defend a little City, having few men in it, againſt a great King that came againſt it, and beſieged it,</hi> Eccl. 9. 14, 15. Surely in the wiſdome of the Lord, who is <hi>only wiſe,</hi> whoſe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is infinite, there may be ſtrong confidence.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Again, <hi>Compare the hatred of the Saints enemies with the love which the Lord bears them.</hi> Great is the hatred of the world, greater is the hatred of the Devil; but oh by infinite degrees greater than either, than both, is the Love of God. The Love of God to believers is very tender, draws out his care towards them; 'tis a love that is unchangeable, and ſo vaſt as paſſes all dimenſions, and underſtanding. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may be emboldened, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that this love will be ten thouſand times more beneficial, than the hatred of any creature can poſſibly be injurious. In the loving kindneſs of God, there is very great ſecurity, <hi>Pſal. 5. 12. For thou Lord
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60678:31"/> wilt bleſs the righteous, with favour wilt thou compaſſe him as with a Shield.</hi> Our enemies indeed may be many, and may hate us with cruel hatred; but their hatred can no more equal the love of God, than their ſtrength can vie with his moſt glorious power.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To ſhew the unreaſonableneſs of the Saints fear, let this be conſidered, <hi>That this God, whoſe power and wiſdom and love are thus beyond compare, is ever with them.</hi> Fear thou not, ſayes God by the Prophet, <hi>for I am with thee,</hi> Iſa. 4. 10. He is not out of the way when his people want him; he is a <hi>preſent help</hi> in the time of need. The Saints need not go far to ſeek their God; he fills the earth as well as heaven, and is alwayes ready to ſhew himſelf ſtrong in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ehalf of thoſe that truſt in him. The Lord is alwayes within hearing; <hi>his eye is upon the righteous, and his ear is open to their cry,</hi> Pſal. 34. 15. He beſets his people behind and before, and layes his hand upon them: ſurely their faith may conclude, ſince God is ſo near them, and does beſet and fence them, that they are in ſafeguard.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The Lord hath engaged by an everlaſting Covenant to be their God:</hi> What, or why therefore ſhould believers fear? <hi>Be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60678:31"/> for I am thy God,</hi> in that forecited place, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41. 10. The Lord ſtands near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly related to the Saints: now 'tis certain, that Relation, though 'tis <hi>minimae entitatis,</hi> yet 'tis <hi>efficaciae maxim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> it hath ſmall enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but great efficacy. He is <hi>their God, their Father, their Husband;</hi> and will he not be a Buckler and a Fortreſs to his children, his Sons eſpouſed ones? Will he not take care of his Jewels, of his portion, of his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar treaſure? will he patiently ſuffer the apple of his eye to be touched? Let the Covenant be ſtudied, and what's im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, in that, <hi>I will be to them a God, and they ſhall be to me a people;</hi> and fear will quickly give way to confidence.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>The Lord intends to glorifie himſelf in his peoples preſervation.</hi> They need not fear, God will not miſs of his glory; he will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, and therefore his people ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred. Gods honour, and the Saints ſafety, are twiſted together. It was a ſtrong argument which <hi>Joſhua</hi> pleaded; If <hi>Iſrael</hi> fly, and the <hi>Canaanites</hi> prevail, then <hi>what wilt thou do for thy great Name?</hi> Joſh. 7. 9. That place in the <hi>Proverbs, The Name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower, the righteous fly unto it and are ſafe,</hi> may not only thus be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, That the power, and faithfulneſs, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60678:32"/> mercy of God, by which he hath made himſelf known as by his name, are a ſafe ſhelter to the righteous; but alſo thus the place may be applyed: God for his Name ſake will be a ſtrong Tower to his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and when they plead his Name, he will glorifie himſelf in their protection. To ſecure his own honour, he will ſecure thoſe whom he hath taken the charge of; they ſhall be ſaved, either <hi>ſub coelo,</hi> or <hi>in coelo;</hi> they ſhall either on earth find a Chamber in the day of calamity, till the indignation be overpaſt; or they ſhall be houſed in the celeſtial Manſions, beyond the fear or poſſibility of danger.</p>
               <p>Thus have I demonſtrated the unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of the Saints fear. The Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of this Doctrine follows.</p>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>USE I.</head>
                  <p>Although I would have you fearleſs of ſuffering, yet ſome Cautions are very needful to be given you. Raſhneſs is not a Grace, though Chriſtian fortitude and courage is.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Take heed <hi>of augmenting your ſufferings needleſly by want of wiſdom.</hi> Died <hi>Abner</hi> as a fool dieth? Do believers ſuffer as fools
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60678:32"/> ſuffer? When Chriſt tells his Diſciples, that he ſent them forth as ſheep among wolves, <hi>He bids them to be wiſe as Serpents, to beware of men,</hi> and uſes much what the ſame Language that one of his Prophets did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. <hi>Jer. 9. 4, 5. Take ye heed every one of his Neighbour, truſt ye not in any brother, for every brother will utterly ſupplant, and every neighbour will walk with ſlanders, and they will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eceive every one his neighbour, and will not ſpeak the truth; they have taught their tongue to ſpeak lies, and they weary themſelves to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit iniquity.</hi> Be wary what, and to whom you ſpeak: In evil times the prudent keep ſilence; when men are made offenders for a word. Do not heartily credit every pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour, there are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>y falſe brethren, who though they ſpeak you fair, have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations in their heart. Beg wiſdom of God that he would guide you with his eye.</p>
                  <p>But let not a wily, and ſelfiſh heart im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon you, and call cowardiſe by the name of diſcretion. If thy heart be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the world, and thou art loath to part with thy enjoyments that are earthly, for the enjoyment of Chriſt and Glory; if thou lookeſt upon earthly things as ſutable, and ſpiritual with a ſtrange eye:
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60678:33"/> ſuſpect thy wiſdom to come not from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and that 'twill be found folly in the end.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Take heed of ſuffering as an evil doer.</hi> You may in all likelihood have much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſpoken againſt you; but if it be falſly, 'tis well enough. That counſel and cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Apoſtle, is much to be obſerved, 1 <hi>Pet. 4. 15. But let none of you ſuffer as a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, or as a thief, or as a buſie body in other mens matters.</hi> You muſt indeed expect to go through evil report, as well as good, and diſhonour as well as honour, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 8. But do not by any ſiniſter aimes, by any unwarrantable practice, give conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence juſt cauſe to reproach you, as well as your enemies. If you are convinced and ſuffer as evil doers, if covetouſneſs, lying, injuſtice, ſedition, rebellion, be juſtly laid to your charge, you will not ſuffer alone, but the Goſpel, and your brethren who are innocent, will be branded for your ſakes. Oh let there be nothing of a crime in your ſuffering; purely let it be for the ſake of purity in worſhip, and purity of life; then the greater comfort will redound to you, and advantage to the Church of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Take heed of vain glory in your ſufferings.</hi> That glory that is but vain, is not worth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60678:33"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he ſeeking, much leſs the ſuffering to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. Though a ſufferer be in a low con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, yet he is in great danger of being pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t up with pride. If you deſign the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing of your own eſteem, and deſire to be pointed at as thoſe that are reſolute and conſtant, you are Self's, and not Chriſts Martyrs. How far may pride and vain glory carry an unſound profeſſour? He <hi>may give all his goods to feed the poor,</hi> nay <hi>his body to be burned,</hi> and yet in all this ſeek himſelf, and be deſtitute of love to Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 3. As the Apoſtle ſayes, <hi>Phil. 2. 3. Let nothing be done,</hi> ſo may I ſay, let nothing be ſuffered <hi>through ſtrife or vain glory.</hi> 'Tis a poor thing to be admired and commended of men, if the Lord does not commend you. If you ſeek not <hi>his</hi> appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, and that honour which comes from <hi>him,</hi> you may ſuffer here and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally beſides. Aim not therefore at ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, or any ſuch carnal, by, and baſe end: but let this be your deſign, that <hi>Chriſt may be magnified by you, whether it be by life or by death,</hi> Phil. 1. 20.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Take heed of being Saints in ſhew, and ſuffering in a good Cauſe with an evil conſcience.</hi> Hypocritical profeſſors are in a very bad caſe; becauſe <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> the world hates
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60678:34"/> them; becauſe <hi>hypocritical</hi> they are hated by the Lord: They have a form of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, therefore the world ſtrikes at them; they deny the power of godlineſs, therefore God will not ſecure them. Oh therefore beg an upright heart, and be ſure to walk in truth. Cover no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with the vail of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie any luſt that you judg pleaſing or profitable; but be <hi>Jewes</hi> inwardly, <hi>Iſraelites</hi> indeed, not contenting your ſelves with a name that you are alive; this you may have, and yet be dead in ſin, and at laſt damn'd for it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <head>USE II.</head>
                  <p>Let me diſſwade you from fearing any thing that may befall you for following the Lord Jeſus. And let theſe two things be thought on, that fear is both, a <hi>Torment,</hi> and a <hi>Snare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Fear is a torment.</hi> The fearful heart is moved, as the leaves are with the wind. What anguiſh ſeizeth upon the timorous ſpirit at the report of evil tydings? how doth it ſink into an hopeleſs kind of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection? and ſo is made more bare and naked unto the ſtroke and dint of calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which are invading.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:60678:34"/>2. <hi>Fear is a ſnare,</hi> Prov. 29. 25. One that fears an arm of fleſh, will ſoon be hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away from God, and into almoſt any unlawful courſes, which by his carnal and diſturbed mind are judged to have a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency: to his preſervation. <hi>Peter</hi> fears, and denyes Chriſt, and not only ſo, but falls a curſing; ſwearing that he did not know him. How is he foiled through fear, who before ſaid, <hi>Though all are offended and forſake thee, yet will not I. Cranmer</hi> fears, and againſt his Conſcience ſubſcribes to Popery; and anathematizes the Hereſie of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> thoſe reſtorers of the Goſpel, and of pure and undefiled Religion, which had a long time lay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> buryed by the prevailing of Antichriſt. <hi>Spira</hi> fears the looſing of his eſtate, the beggering of his wife and children, the hazarding of his life, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces the Proteſtant Religion, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently was ſeiz'd upon by the Pangs of deſpair; and to the terrour and aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all about him, ſpake as if he had been in Hell it ſelf, even while he was alive. Oh therefore be afraid of being afraid; if this paſſion prevail, you may quickly fall ſo foully, as to make you weep bitterly, if not eternally.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="application">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:60678:35"/>
                  <head>USE III.</head>
                  <p>I ſhall conclude with ſeveral Antidotes againſt this ſinful and enſnaring fear of ſufferings. The Antidotes are theſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. One Antidote is <hi>a well grounded aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the love of God.</hi> By this love, fear will be caſt out. The Apoſtle was ſo far from being afraid, <hi>that he gloryed in tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and the reaſon was, becauſe <hi>the love of God,</hi> that is, the ſenſe and perſwaſion of it, <hi>was ſhed abroad in his heart by the Holy Ghoſt which was given to him,</hi> Rom. 5. 3, 5. When we know that God is <hi>ours,</hi> we may conclude that afflictions, troubles, and death are ours, that evil men and evil Angels too are ours, that is, working out our good, though contrary to their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The enemies of believers are but as ſo many Scullions to ſcour them, and make them look the brighter. The aſſured Chriſtian concludes, that greater is he that is in him, than he that is in the World, and therefore he is undaunted. Heark, how confidently the Saints of old ſpake, who knew the God of <hi>Jacob</hi> was theirs, and with them, <hi>Pſal. 46. 1, 2. God is our refuge and ſtrength, a very preſent help in trouble;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60678:35"/> therefore will we not fear, though the earth be removed, though the mountains be carryed into the midſt of the Seas.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Give diligence therefore to make your Calling and Election ſure; bring your Grace to the Touchſtone of the Scripture, that the truth thereof may be evident; pray that the Lord would ſearch you, and lead you out of every evil way; and that his Spirit may bear witneſs with your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits that you are indeed his Children.</p>
                  <p n="2">2, A ſecond Antidote againſt fear, <hi>is a clear Conſcience.</hi> A pacified and purified Conſcience, will make the heart very couragious. The Heathen Poet could ſay,
<q>
                        <p>—<hi>Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> murus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>aenius eſto; Nil conſcire ſibi, nulla palleſcere culpa.</hi> Horat. Epiſt. 2.</p>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Brazen Wall is not a greater ſecurity than an unſpotted conſcience. And <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> tells us, <hi>that a righteous man is bold as a Lion.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> when he was preſſed out of meaſure by the weight of troubles, above ſtrength, inſomuch that he deſpaired even of life; was he diſmay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? No; ſo far from that, that he rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. This was ſtrange indeed: What
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60678:36"/> might be the cauſe of his gladneſs, when ſenſe being judg, his condition was ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding doleful? <hi>Our rejoycing is this,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>even the teſtimony of our conſcience, that in ſimplicity, and godly ſincerity, not with fleſhly wiſdome, but by the grace of God we have had our converſation in the world,</hi> 2 Cor. 1. 12. Make not therefore, eſpecially in troublous times, any breach upon conſcience, by cloſing with temptations, for at that breach fear will aſſault you.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A third Antidote againſt fear, <hi>is truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in God. David</hi> ſayes, <hi>What time I am afraid, I will truſt in thee,</hi> Pſal. 56. 3. There's the diſtemper, <hi>fear,</hi> and the remedy againſt it, <hi>faith in God.</hi> So Pſal. 112. 7. <hi>He ſhall not be afraid of evil tydings, his heart is fixed:</hi> What fixes the righteous mans heart? <hi>Truſting in the Lord.</hi> Pray for the increaſe of faith: be well acquainted with the promiſes, wherein God hath ſaid he will be <hi>a ſhield, an hiding place, a covert, a ſtrong Tower, a Saviour;</hi> and theſe promiſes will be as food for your faith to live upon, and to grow ſtrong by. But be ſure let your truſting in God be joyned <hi>with the doing of good,</hi> Pſal. 37. 3. with a deſire and deſign to pleaſe him; elſe he will reject your confidence as preſumption, and you ſhall not proſper in it.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:60678:36"/>4. A Fourth Antidote againſt fear, <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> calling upon God. David</hi> when he was in danger, cryes that he may be lead to the Rock that was higher than he; when ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with enemies <hi>he gave himſelf unto prayer,</hi> Pſal. 109. 4. and by this means he got above his fears and terrours. He tells us how effectual prayer was, <hi>Pſal. 34. 4. I ſought the Lord, and he heard me, and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me from all my fears.</hi> The Coneys are a feeble folk, but have their dwelling among the Rocks: You may learn a great deal of wiſdome from thoſe little creatures. By Faith and Prayer you ſhould be work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſelves further into the Rock of Ages, and that Rock you will find im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. A Fifth Antidote againſt fear <hi>is an heavenly Converſation.</hi> They who are much above, that have their Treaſure in that place, where neither moth corrupteth, nor thief approacheth, will not be afraid of priſons, of being robb'd, of being ſlain for the Teſtimony of Jeſus. Their ſouls can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be touched, their beſt riches are dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and out of their enemies reach; their adverſaries cannot by diſtraining take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their glory or grace from them: and when this life is done, they will enter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60678:37"/> that life which is infinitely better.</p>
                  <p>They who walk cloſely with God, and whoſe hearts as an heave-offering are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently given to him, <hi>being lifted up in his wayes,</hi> who every day do take ſeveral turns <hi>in the City that hath foundations;</hi> who often think of the glorious prize, and what it will be to be perfectly holy, and moſt fully ſatisfied in the uninterrupted and never ending enjoyment of God; ſuch will be indifferent what on earth they meet with; they will not be afraid of what man can do, ſince when their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies do their worſt, they do their beſt; for when they take away their lives, they do but ſend them thither, where they long and groan earneſtly to be received, and to make their everlaſting abode.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle informs us, <hi>That they who mind earthly things are enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 3. 18, 19. They feel not its crucifying vertue, they are afraid of it, they are offended at it: but as for himſelf, <hi>whoſe converſation was in heaven, and who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually from thence was looking for a Saviour, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> he knew how to be abaſed, how to be hungry, now to ſuffer need, and learned in whatever ſtate he was therewith to be contented, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 11, 12. compared with <hi>v.</hi> 20. of <hi>ch.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:60678:37"/>6. A ſixth Antidote againſt fear, <hi>is a due conſideration who your enemies and troublers are.</hi> Bring them into the Sanctuary, and there take a view of them, weigh them in the ballance, and themſelves with all their power, will be found ſo light, that you will conclude that to be a very vain fear, which ſuch vain and weak creatures as they are, do raiſe in you.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Your enemies <hi>are but men;</hi> let them do their worſt, their moſt, they can but kill the body. <hi>Ceaſe ye from man,</hi> ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, for wherein is he to be accounted of.</hi> The hand of man, as 'tis not able to ſuppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t us, ſo neither to throw us down; and conſequently he doth no more deſerve to be feared, than to be truſted in by us.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Your enemies are men <hi>whom the Lord hates</hi> and ſets his face againſt. He or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains his arrows againſt the perſecutors, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. 13. God ſhall ſhoot at them, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſhall they be wounded. He is more angry at them, than they can be enraged againſt you; and it will not be long ere he eaſe himſelf and you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oo of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome oppreſſours, <hi>Iſa. 1. 24. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith the Lord, the Lord of Hoſts, the mighty one of Iſrael, Ah I will caſe me of my
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60678:38"/> adverſaries, and avenge me of my enemies.</hi> Fear becomes <hi>them</hi> that have ſuch a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God their enemy, not <hi>you</hi> that have him to be your Father and Defender.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="doctrine">
               <head>The Third Doctrine.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Among other troubles, ſome believers endure bonds and impriſonment.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>In the Catalogue of ſufferings, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment is reckoned by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Heb. 11. 36. And others had tryal of cruel mockings and ſcourgings, yea moreover of bonds and impriſonment.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſpeaks after this manner, <hi>Acts 20. 22, 23. And now behold I go bound in the ſpirit unto Jeruſalem, not knowing the things that ſhall befall me there, ſave that the holy Ghoſt witneſſeth in every City, ſaying that bonds and afflictions abide me.</hi> The members of Chriſt, though made free by their Head, yet may have fetters put upon them by unreaſonable men. In the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment of the Saints, two things are to be conſidered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Their confinement, and the reſtraint that is laid upon them.</hi> Liberty is agreeable to Nature, 'tis therefore a great tryal to loſe it; and the cloſer the impriſonment is,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60678:38"/> Nature accounts it the more irkſome. <hi>To have lovers and friends and acquaintance put far away,</hi> may well be lookt upon as a great affliction. To be within double doors, and thoſe doubly barr'd; to look through I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron grates, is a condition which needs ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thing from above to ſweeten it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Their being numbred among evil doers,</hi> is another part of the impriſoned believers tryal. As the Lord himſelf <hi>was numbred among the tranſgreſſours,</hi> Iſa. 53. 12. ſo are his Priſoners. The ſame Gaol contains Thieves and Harlots, and the Witneſſes of Jeſus, their innocency is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, and things that they know not are laid to their charge: But the Lord hath promiſed, that within a while, <hi>their righteouſneſſe ſhall be brought forth as the light, and their judgment as the Noon day,</hi> Pſal. 37. 6.</p>
               <p>Now the Reaſon why the Saints are impriſoned by their enemies, is twofold.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That they may be puniſhed.</hi> If their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies can go no further, they will go thus far, and hereby they think to take ſome revenge upon them; though they little imagine what a ſweet place they ſend the Saints to; God turns their revenge into a kindneſſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That they may be hindred from doing
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60678:39"/> good,</hi> is another Reaſon why the Saints are confined. They went about doing good while Liberty was enjoyed, therefore they are reſtrained, and their feet made faſt, that they may no longer be thus em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, though it be as their Lord and Maſter himſelf was, in the dayes of his fleſh. But it is the application of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine I principally intend.</p>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>USE I.</head>
                  <p>Of Direction, how the Saints ſhould behave themſelves when they are impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned. Their carriage I ſhall direct in theſe particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They muſt carry themſelves <hi>humbly before God.</hi> Sin and the deſert of it ſhould be called to remembrance; and how a worſe place than a priſon hath been juſtly merited. You ſhould lament your not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving of Liberty while you had it, your unprofitableneſs, your unuſefulneſs, that ſo little good was done, when you had opportunities in your hands. The Croſſe indeed that's laid upon you, is a badge of honour; and yet withall there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what <hi>medicinal</hi> in it, which argues remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of ſpiritual diſtempers that ſhould be
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60678:39"/> matter of humiliation. The more hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and contrite you are, the more viſits you are likely to have from the High and Lofty One, who inhabiteth Eternity: <hi>He dwells with the lowly, that he may revive the ſpirit of the humble, and that he may revive the heart of the contrite ones,</hi> Iſa. 57. 15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. You muſt carry your ſelves <hi>meekly and modeſtly towards your enemies;</hi> you muſt bleſs them that curſe you, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y for your deſpightful perſecutors, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 44. Call not the Wild-fire of your own paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the name of zeal: and ever remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that excellent and divine Maxime, <hi>The wrath of man worketh not the righteouſneſſe of God,</hi> Jam. 1. 20. Imitate the perfect Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, who when he was reviled, reviled not again, when he ſuffer'd, he threatned not, but committed himſelf to him that judgeth righteouſly. Meekneſs and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity will be lovely and convincing too, in the eyes of your adverſaries, and they may be brought to acknowledge, if Chriſt hath any followers, that <hi>you</hi> do moſt reſemble him, and are likely to be the perſons.</p>
                  <p n="3">3: <hi>Be not daunted at impriſonment.</hi> Look with another kind of countenance than thoſe do that ſuffer for evil doing. Let not your joyes be ſo low as to be in the power
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60678:40"/> of creatures to rob you of them. Shew by your chearfulneſs you have choſen that good part which men cannot take away from you. Check your ſpirits when they begin to deſpond, and ſay with <hi>David, Pſal. 43. ult. Why art thou caſt down O my ſoul? and why art thou diſquieted within me? Hope thou in God, for I ſhall yet praiſe him, who is the health of my countenance, and my God.</hi> And that you may be thus fortified, beg that the Lord would ſtrengthen you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his glorious power with all might, unto all patience and long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with joyfulneſs, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 11.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Since you are taken off from other buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, abound the more in duty.</hi> Now the Throne of Grace ſhould be often viſited; and the Word which ſtrengthens in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which revives in heavineſs, ſhould be more than ever ſearched into. It is meet that <hi>Priſons</hi> ſhould be <hi>Houſes of Prayer.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſequeſtred from the World, you ſhould be the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re with God. Pull up all the Flood-gates, and let the ſtream of your affections run with an holy violence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him: Ever be telling him what you need, what you deſire, and be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by the promiſe he hath made <hi>to ſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the weary, and to repleniſh every ſorrowful ſoul,</hi> Jer. 31. 25.</p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:60678:40"/>
                  <p>Fellowſhip with God will make ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude pleaſant; you will find, though alone, that you have the beſt company. If you are continually almoſt ſpeaking to God by ſupplication and thanksgiving, and hearing what he ſpeaks to you, by his Word, and Providences, and Spirit, you will have reaſon to profeſs, that a <hi>Priſon</hi> is one of the beſt places of abode, next to the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> and the <hi>New Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Let impriſonment be improved ſo as to further your progreſs in ſanctification.</hi> Ranſack every corner of your hearts. Deal much more ſeverely with your luſts than men can deal with you; cry out with violence againſt your fleſhly and worldly inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. 'Tis ſin that deads and impriſons your Spirits; the more ſanctified you are, the more you will be at liberty. Tell the Lord, and ſpeak it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>m your very hearts, that ſin is the worſt of all your adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and that the remainders of the old man are worſe than any fetters in the world. Never let the Lord al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>, till you find the body of death pining and dying ſenſibly away, the world as a contemptible thing more under your feet, and your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man encreaſing ſtrength, and grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up a pace <hi>to the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt,</hi> Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4. 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:60678:41"/>
                  <head>USE II.</head>
                  <p>Of Conſolation to impriſoned believers. Several things may be ſuggeſted as grounds of comfort and encouragement.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>God can come at his people through barr'd and bolted doors.</hi> No dungeon can keep the Priſoner <hi>cloſe</hi> from him. We read that the Lord came to his Diſciples <hi>the door be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhut, and ſaid, Peace be unto you.</hi> And if he come into the Priſon, the Door being ſhut, and by his Spirit ſay, <hi>Peace be to thee,</hi> the Priſoners heart will leap for joy, he will ſay, not <hi>how dreadful,</hi> but <hi>how delightful</hi> is this place? <hi>this is no other than the Houſe of God, and this is the Gate of Heaven.</hi> Our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, let them diſpoſe of us where and how they pleaſe, cannot keep God from us, or us from God, they cannot ſhut us up from his preſence: and where his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious preſence is vouch ſafed, there is <hi>reſt;</hi> all inconveniences and miſeries are ſo light that they are hardly worth the taking notice of.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>The heart may be enlarged where the body is confined.</hi> The Soul may be brought out of Priſon, when the body is committed to it. In the <hi>Mittimus</hi> the form of Law runs
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60678:41"/> thus, That the Goalet take the <hi>body</hi> of ſuch an one. Verily over the ſpirit they have no power. What believer would not be content to be confined, upon condition his heart might be made more free <hi>to</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, more free <hi>in</hi> duty? upon condition his deſires might ſwell and overflow, and his longings after the God of all grace, might grow much ſtronger than the thirſt of the moſt ſenſual after pleaſures, or of the moſt worldly minded after Gold and Silver.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>The Lord who will condimn thoſe that viſit not the Priſoners,</hi> Mat. 25. <hi>will not fail to viſit them himſelf.</hi> And as they more need refreſhments they ſhall ſurely enjoy them. He will behold them wich a reconciled face, and ſay to them, <hi>I am your light and your ſalvation,</hi> be not terrified with the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the calamitous day wherein you live. The groaning of the priſoner doth pierce the Heavens, and enters into the ear of the Lord of Sabaoth, who will return an anſwer of peace and conſolation.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>The Priſoners of Chriſt are Priſoners of Hope.</hi> They are in but during the King of Saints his pleaſure. If Chriſt ſay, <hi>Come forth,</hi> even a <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſhall break out of a Grave: And if he have the Key of the Grave, ſurely the Keyes of priſons are at
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60678:42"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ommand; they cannot hold any whom he hath a mind to ſet at liberty. Priſons may ſoon grow ſick of the Saints, and vomit them out as the Whale did <hi>Jonah.</hi> However, it will not be long e're the day of glorious liberty, and of full Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on come; and then the adverſaries of the Saints will be bound hand and foot, and thrown into outer darkneſs; and the Saints will have liberty to enter into the Kingdome prepared for them, to ſee God face to face, without any lett from others or themſelves, and to live eternally in <hi>his preſence, where there is fulneſs of joy, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for evermore,</hi> Pſal. 16. ult.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="doctrine">
               <head>The Fourth Doctrine.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Devil is the impriſoner of Believers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>Sayes the Text, <hi>Behold the Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon.</hi> The words may be referred more particularly to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, or more generally to the Saints in <hi>Smyrna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>More particularly to the Miniſters.</hi> As by <hi>One Candleſtick</hi> the whole Body of the Congregation, ſo by <hi>One Angel</hi> the whole company of the Paſtours are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60678:42"/> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you I ſay, and to the reſt in Thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atira,</hi> Rev. 2. 24. That is, unto you the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and the reſt of believers. So here, <hi>The Devil ſhall caſt ſome of</hi> you <hi>into priſon;</hi> that is, <hi>you</hi> who are the Shepherds, that ſo againſt the flock he may have the greater advantage.</p>
               <p>Faithful Miniſters Satan never could, neither can he now endure. He endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours if he can to corrupt them, to puff them up with pride, to draw them aſide by filthy lucre, to make them fall ſome way or other; and he does it with this deſign, that their doctrine may be the loſs heeded, and his Kingdome not ſo much weakned by them. But if he be not able to <hi>corrupt,</hi> he will be induſtrious to <hi>diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage</hi> them. They trouble him, will not let him alone, they will not ſuffer the ſtrong man armed to keep his houſe in peace, but by warning, exhorting, reprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, rebuking the ſecure and ungodly, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to diſpoſſeſs him. No wonder if the Devil wax angry at them, and fling them out of their houſes into places of confinement.</p>
               <p>The Prince of darkneſs would not that theſe <hi>Stars</hi> ſhould ſhine; he would fain have theſe <hi>Candles put under Buſhels<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60678:43"/> Light diſcovers what Satan is, what a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, hateful and hating ſpirit, it diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers what his works be, namely to pollute us, and by polluting to fit us for perdition. Light alſo diſcovers what ſin is, and the unconceivable needfulneſs and excellency of the Lord Jeſus. And hereupon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils Vaſſals, ſeveral of them, are made to bethink themſelves, and <hi>are delivered from the Power of darkneſs, and tranſlated into the Kingdome of the Son of God,</hi> Gol. 1. 13. The joyful ſound of mans ſalvation is harſh in Satans ears; he impriſons therefore the Publiſhers of theſe glad-tydings, and cloſe ſomtimes, that the flock may be edified neither in a publick, nor more private way.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The words may be referred <hi>more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally to the Saints in Smyrna.</hi> Every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt the Devil hates, and would fain tear from him; every ſheep this roat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lion would make his prey; therefore he raiſes perſecution to diſhearten them from following their great Shepherd. Though herein the ſubtle Serpent playes the fool egregiouſly; for the Saints grow more acquainted with their Lord in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, like him the better, and are knit the faſter to him ever after.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:60678:43"/>
               <p>But here it may be enquired, How the Devil doth caſt the Saints into priſon? The Reſolution of this ſhall be in theſe three particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Devil ſtirs up falſe accuſers of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers.</hi> The Name which the Holy Ghoſt gives him in the Text is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>a calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niator,</hi> or <hi>falſe accuſer.</hi> He accuſeth the Brethren before God, and his Inſtruments at his inſtigation do it before men. He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired falſe witneſſes againſt Chriſt; he doth the ſame againſt Chriſts followers. This unclean Spirit is utterly alienated both from <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Love.</hi> Malicious lyes, eſpecially againſt the Brotherhood, he is the Father of: Words that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpake, nay, which to ſpeak is againſt their conſcience; Deeds that they never did, nay which they abhor to do, are not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding fathered upon them by the children of the <hi>Father of lyes and lyars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Devil cheriſhes in the minds of his ſervants unreaſonable jealouſies and ſurmizes concerning Saints; and this is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother matter which occaſions their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment; they are lookt upon as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous perſons, and that 'tis inconvenient and unſafe to have them at liberty. As the Primitive Chriſtians had the skins of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60678:44"/> brute beaſts put upon them, and then were worryed. So believers are repreſented by Satan to the minds of their enemies, as <hi>enemies to Government,</hi> as <hi>Turners of the world upſide down,</hi> as <hi>thoſe that would ſet the Nation in a combuſtion.</hi> But oh! how far are they from deſerving ſuch a Character! They pray earneſtly and deſire heartily, under authority <hi>to live quiet and peaceable lives in all godlineſs and honeſty.</hi> They are indeed the Diſciples of the Prince of peace, and make conſcience of following after <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>holineſs,</hi> without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 14.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Devil hightens the enmity againſt, and hatred of piety, that naturally is in the minds of the ungodly;</hi> ſo that it breaks out into acts of cruelty and injuſtice. Although corrupted Nature of it ſelf be very furious, yet 'tis more violent when the Devil joyns with it. He can ſet an edge on the luſts of men, and make them the more impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. When concupiſcence is blown up by an unclean Spirit, how doth it burn and flame then? When pride is hightned by a proud Devil, how uncontroulable is it by any adviſe or conſideration? and in like manner, when envy, hatred and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and uncharitableneſs (as they are put
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60678:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> together in the Letany) are made more keen by a ſpightful Satan: No wonder if the tongues of the ungodly prove ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and their hands ſtrike at believers liberty, if not at their lives.</p>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>USE I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of counſel and advice to perſecutors.</hi> I know not but this Book may light into the hands of one of them. Underſtand O enemy, whoever thou art, that thou haſt a friend at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> houſe who wiſhes thee well, who prayes for thy welfare as well as his own, who would ſtop thee in thy pernicious way; not ſo much for the Saints ſake as for thy own: for thou doeſt thy ſelf, not them, the greateſt miſchief. Let not O ye perſecutors, your rage ſtop your eares, be a little in cool blood, and hearken unto theſe two words of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Conſider then by whom you are acted. The Devil caſts the Saints into priſon, whoſe inſtruments and ſervants then are you? Is there not a better Maſter to be ſerved, a better work to be employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about? What thanks do you think our Lord Chriſt will give you for the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60678:45"/> ſervice you do to this deſtroyer.</p>
                  <p>But you will ſay, <hi>'Tis zeal puts us upon what we do, and we hope we do God and his Church good ſervice:</hi> Yes, ſo the Jews thought they ſerved God, when they ſet themſelves againſt his Son: and Chriſt himſelf foretold this, <hi>Joh. 16. 2. They ſhall put you out of the Synagogues, they ſhall excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate you, yea the time cometh, that wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſoever killeth you will think that he doth God good ſervice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>O that you would become friends to your ſelves, by being friends unto the Saints.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes that before his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>he was exceeding mad</hi> againſt the Lords Diſciples, <hi>Acts</hi> 26. 11. He ſhewed himſelf to be exceeding mad indeed, to ſet himſelf againſt them that were ſo dear to the Lord Jeſus. But at laſt he is reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to his wits, he is cured of that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting phrenzy that poſſeſt and acted him, and then <hi>he preached that faith, which once he endeavoured to deſtroy,</hi> Gal. 1. 23. O that you would become propagatours of that Goſpel which now you oppoſe and hinder from being preached.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:60678:45"/>
                  <head>USE II.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Of conſolation to the priſoners of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Think how weak the Devil is, if compared with the Captain of your Salvation.</hi> Chriſt has fought with this old Dragon and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him, he has tried his ſtrength, and has been much too hard for him: He has taken the Devil captive and holds him in a chain. As the great Emperour and Conquerour <hi>Tamerlane</hi> kept <hi>Bajazet</hi> the Turkiſh King in an iron cage: So the Lord Jeſus having ſubdued Satan keeps him in ſhackles; he cannot ſtir to deſtroy a Swine, much leſs to moleſt a Saint without Chriſts leave; and will he give the Devil leave to do any thing to his faithful followers that may be really to their prejudice?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There is leſs danger when Satan rages, then when he flatters; 'tis better he ſhould caſt you into priſon for well doing, then draw you into his ſnar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and unto the commiſſion of evil. His pleaſing temptations are moſt hard to be reſiſted. When you ſee him furious and play the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60678:46"/> Devil indeed, as 'tis a ſign he has loſt you, ſo his enmity being more perceivable, it will make you fly to that <hi>Merciful and Faithful High Prieſt who knowes how to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour them that are tempted,</hi> Heb. 2. ult. And beſides his hatred at ſuch a time being ſo viſibly diſcovered, 'twill make you more ſober and vigilant ever after; and to get on the armour, that you may ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all his wiles all his devices.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>The Devil may have great wrath, but he hath but a ſhort time,</hi> Rev. 12. 12. He is the more buſie becauſe he is aware that your warfare will ſhortly be at an end; and that the ſpiritual combatants, within a few yeares will be Conquerours and Crowned. Happy thoſe that are above! Devils cannot come at them! they know not what temptation means. 'Tis no more poſſible for any of Satans fiery darts to hit any of the Saints in glory, than for an Arrow that we ſhoot upward into the aire to hit the Sun in the firmament. Now you Saints that are below, will come to be above ſhortly, <hi>Romans 13. 11. Your ſalvation growes nearer and nearer every day.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="doctrine">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:60678:46"/>
               <head>The Fifth Doctrine.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saints are impriſoned that they may be tried.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>The Devil, ſayes the text, ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon that <hi>ye may be tried.</hi> The word in the original is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>that ye may be tempted.</hi> Now trial, or tem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is ſometimes taken in a <hi>bad</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in a <hi>good ſenſe,</hi> and the text may be underſtood either way.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Tryal or temptation may be taken in a bad ſenſe as referred to the Devil.</hi> Certainly he by impriſoning believers deſignes to make them weary of their Lords yoak; he would fain have them murmure and be impatient under reſtraint, and draw them to ſome ſinful compliance, to the wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their conſciences for the regaining of their liberty. He endeavours to make them grow diſcontented, &amp; quarrel at the Lords diſpenſations; that their enemies which are vile, and the baſeſt of men ſhould yet proſper, and themſelves in the mean time be expoſed to ſo many hardſhips and inconveniencies notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the integrity of their hearts, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60678:47"/> the unblamableneſs of their converſations.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Trial or temptation may be taken in a good ſenſe, as referred to Gods permitting the Saints to be thus exerciſed.</hi> He hath certainly a wiſe, and gracious, and holy end in it. 'Tis true, <hi>God cannot be tempted with evil, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tempteth he any man,</hi> Jam. 1. 13. And yet 'tis expreſly affirmed that God did tempt <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 20. 1. How ſhall theſe two places be reconciled? I anſwer, That temptation ſpoken of by the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> is to be underſtood concerning <hi>drawing away and enticing to wickedneſs,</hi> v. 14. of ch. 1. And thus God tempteth not; he neither infuſeth, nor excites any ſinful inclinations in the heart of man, but ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forbids ſin, and will ſeverely puniſh it. Thus men are tempted by Satan, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by their own luſts. But that temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſpoken of by <hi>Moſes,</hi> is as much as <hi>trying or making proof of Abrahams ſincerity:</hi> and thus to tempt, is not at all unbecom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or inconſiſtent with the Lords holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and goodneſs: and when he ſuffers believers to be impriſoned, 'tis for their try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al that he does it.</p>
               <p>Now here I ſhall firſt ſhew, What of the Saints is tryed by impriſonment, and ſufferings of the like nature. Secondly,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60678:47"/> to what end they are thus tryed.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place, <hi>What of the Saints is tryed by impriſonment,</hi> and ſufferings of the like nature. Firſt, <hi>their Faith.</hi> Secondly, <hi>their Love.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>their ſubjection and obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Their Faith is tryed.</hi> They that can looſe what they have for Chriſt, it argues a full perſwaſion that Chriſt is better than their earthly enjoyments, and that they believe there is ſuch a <hi>fulneſs in him</hi> as can make up all their loſſes. Such eſteem the promiſes of eternal bleſſings, exceeding great and precious, who are reſolved to embrace them whatever they fling away beſides. When in a good Cauſe we lightly eſteem liberty and outward accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, it ſhewes we have that faith <hi>which is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of things not ſeen,</hi> Heb. 11. 1. Our faith gives a ſubſiſtence to, and mightily realli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth thoſe things which as yet we have only the hopes of enjoying; and makes the great things of another world evident, though not to be ſeen or poſſeſſed till hereafter. Faith is a noble grace, it glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies God exceedingly; when a man upon the Lords word, will conſent to quit all that's near and dear to him, in expectation
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60678:48"/> of a Kingdom and Glory which no man alive ever ſaw.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By impriſonment and other ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings <hi>Believers Love is tryed.</hi> They who can undervalue Liberty, and livelyhood, and life, for the ſake of the Son of God, may boldly ſay as <hi>Peter</hi> did in another caſe, <hi>Lord thou knoweſt all things, thou knoweſt that we love thee,</hi> 'Tis manifeſt they love the Lord Jeſus in ſincerity. But if when the world and Chriſt ſtand in competition, we hold to the world, and deſpiſe the Lord, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly our love is but a painted, not a real fire. Love is a Grace of an uniting nature. The Hiſtory tells us, <hi>That the ſoul of Jonathan was knit to David, and he loved him as his own ſoul:</hi> and we find that the diſpleaſure which <hi>Saul</hi> had conceived againſt <hi>David,</hi> and the danger that <hi>Jonathan</hi> was in, for his affection ſake, could not cool, much leſs quench his love. If we love our Lord, our ſouls will be knit to him; and troubles will be ſo far from diſſolving the union, that they will cauſe us to cling the cloſer, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p the faſter about him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By impriſonment, and ſufferings of the like nature, there is a tryal made of <hi>believers ſubjection and obedience.</hi> When they will <hi>do</hi> for God, though preſently <hi>ſuffering</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:60678:48"/> for God follow; this argues they have learned to deny their own wills, and taken the Word and will of God as their guide and Rule. When they regard the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God above the commands of men, are awed by the threatnings of God more than the threats of men, and dread Gods diſpleaſure more than mans anger; this is a demonſtration that they have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto Chriſts Scepter, and that the Promiſe of the Covenant is fulfilled, <hi>Heb. 8. 10. I will put my Lawes into their minds, and write them in their hearts, and I will be to them a God, and they ſhall be to me a people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſecond place I am to tell you, <hi>for what end God will have his Saints thus tryed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That the truth of their Grace may be evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent;</hi> and great peace muſt be the conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant of that evidence. When their gold is tryed in the fire, and gliſters the more, ſhines the brighter, they may be pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced rich indeed. The man that is rich in the World, <hi>hath no reaſon to glory in his riches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> for he is but a beggar in compariſon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are tryed <hi>that Satan may be ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</hi> He can no longer ſay that the Saints are mercenary or ſelfiſh, when ſelf is thus denyed, when peace of conſcience is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the greateſt outward peace
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60678:49"/> and proſperity; and ſo the inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove may be ſecured, they put it to the venture what the world can do to them, or take from them. The Lord may ſay to Satan (and this accuſer of the brethren have nothing to reply) <hi>Haſt thou conſidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my ſuffering Servants, how perfect and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right they be? They fear God, and eſchew evil, though by departing from evil they make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a prey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Believers are tryed, <hi>that God who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds them may be honoured.</hi> The Lord is with them in the furnace; he keeps them like the Buſh in the midſt of the flaming fire, unconſumed. He ſhewes his wiſdome and grace, in ſo tempering the furnace, as that it is both tolerable, and alſo effectual unto their refining. The Saints have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant cauſe readily to acknowledge, that their ſupport in trouble, their benefit by trouble, and their deliverance out of trouble, is wholly to be aſcribed unto God: and he is glorified by this, which is ſo juſt an acknowledgment.</p>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>USE I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Admonition to unſound Profeſſours.</hi> Be reſtleſs till you are ſearched and changed
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60678:49"/> ſo, as to have truth in your inward parts; elſe you will never abide the tryal: in the time of temptation, your ſandy foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will deceive you; <hi>your building will fall, and great will be the fall of it,</hi> Mat. 7. 27.</p>
                  <p>You will fall away <hi>further from God, more f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ully into ſin, more deep into hell;</hi> and all theſe falls will be great and dreadful.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. You that are unſound, in times of tryal wil fall away further from God. Some of you, though never brought quite home, yet have been almoſt perſwaded, have been not far from the Kingdome of Heaven. But all this common work, if you reſt in it, will dye away; when Chriſt puts you upon ſuffering, you will forſake him. <hi>Suffer</hi> is an hard word, who can bear it? And when you leave the Lord, you bid farewel to the Father of mercies; the God of love, and of all grace, the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of living waters, the Prince of peace, the only Saviour. Well may I cry out, Oh how much folly is there in back-ſlid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing!</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>You will fall more foully into ſin.</hi> God may quickly throw the Reins out of his hands upon the neck of corrupted Nature; and whither may you be carryed? Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatizing profeſſors often turn moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60678:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> they out-run, as to riot &amp; exceſs, the wretchest hat never pretended to Religion. The Conſcience that was once awakened, if it fall aſleep again, ſleeps more ſoundly. The heart that was once reſtrain'd from ſin that reſtraint being gone, is more eager to commit iniquity than before. Nay, 'tis ſomtimes obſerved, that backſliding pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> become cruel perſecutors of thoſe wayes which once were forwardly owned by them. If this be not the unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable ſin, I am ſure it comes to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry brink of it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>You will fall more deep into Hell at laſt.</hi> Chriſt tells us that <hi>the laſt end of ſuch is worſe than their beginning,</hi> Mat. 12. 45. and that both as to ſin, and as to puniſhment. How large will be the Vial of wrath to be emptied upon Apoſtates heads? how hot their place in the Lake that burns with fire and brimſtone? Thoſe, that as the Apoſtle ſpeaks <hi>are twice dead, pluckt up by the roots,</hi> Jude 12. The ſecond death will be more terrible to them, they will be eternal fewel to a more furious flame. The ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Saints, whether impriſonment, or death, are not worthy to be named the ſame day, with everlaſting confinement to outer darkneſs, and ſuffering in the higheſt
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60678:50"/> degree and fulleſt meaſure eternal damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Conſider this ye hypocrites that are rotten at heart, that have God in your mouthes, but he is far from your Reins: On how long will it be ere you attain to uprightneſs!</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <head>USE II.</head>
                  <p>Of Encouragement to the Saints when they are exerciſed with Tryals.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>The Lord hath promiſed to keep you when you are tryed.</hi> He may fan and winnow, but not a grain of corn ſhall fall to the ground ſo as to be loſt. That Scripture is very obſervable, <hi>Rev. 3. 10. Becauſe thou haſt kept the word of my patience, I alſo will keep thee from the hour of temptation, which ſhall come upon all the world, to try them that dwell upon the earth.</hi> He will keep from the hour of temptation, that is, from the prevalency of, and corruption by temptation in that hour. But then you muſt be ſure to keep his Word, which is called the Word of his patience, becauſe it propoſes Chriſt as an example of patience, and layes an injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon you to be like him. And if you look upon this word, as your <hi>food,</hi> as your <hi>phyſick,</hi> as your <hi>treaſure,</hi> as your <hi>armour,</hi> as your <hi>heritage,</hi> I hope you will look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as well deſerving to be kept by you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:60678:51"/>2. <hi>Your tryals will make you to grow in grace.</hi> Grace is of that nature that it increaſes and gathers ſtrength by exerciſe. As the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes Oyl by being drawn out did multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; ſo Grace is augmented, not dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, by being uſed. Hark to the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 5. 3, 4 5. Knowing that tribulation wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth patience;</hi> not only tryeth patience, but worketh patience; <hi>and patience experience, and experience hope, and hope maketh not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</hi> The righteous by tryals and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are not ſtopt as diſcouraged perſons, <hi>but hold on their way,</hi> nay not only hold on, but grow and go ſtronger: <hi>and they that have clean hands ſhall wax ſtronger and ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> Job 17. 9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>After you have endured tryal, you ſhall be own'd and crown'd,</hi> Jam. 1. 12. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that endureth temptation, for when he is try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he ſhall receive the Crown of life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that love him.</hi> And that Crown when received will make all pains, and diſgrace, and ſufferings to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="doctrine">
               <head>The Sixth Doctrine.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The tribulation of Believers will not laſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, after ten dayes, that is, a ſhort time, a period will be put to it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:60678:51"/>
               <p>Ye ſhall have tribulation ten dayes. The Holy Ghoſt reckons by <hi>dayes,</hi> not years, and according to the uſual manner, in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a certain number is put for an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, ten dayes for a few dayes. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 17. calls the troubles of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers not only <hi>light afflictions,</hi> but affirms they are <hi>but for a moment;</hi> and becauſe they are but for a moment, ſurely much the lighter.</p>
               <p>The Arguments to confirm this Doctrine are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. One ſhall be drawn <hi>from the deſire in Chriſt the Head to have his members with him.</hi> Therefore they ſhall not long be abſent from him; and when they are with him, no troubles at all ſhall be their compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Chriſt in the dayes of his fleſh prayed thus, <hi>Joh. 17. 24. Father I will that thoſe alſo whom thou haſt given me, be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory, which thou haſt given me, for thou lovedſt me before the foundation of the world.</hi> Chriſt is now gone to his father, and he hath prepared Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for the Saints, and thoſe Manſions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall not be long empty. Believers groan to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e cloathed upon with their houſe which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from Heaven; to be abſent from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, and to be preſent with the Lord. The
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60678:52"/> Lord Jeſus deſires, and hath prayed for their company. Surely it will not be long before thoſe who are ſo mutually deſirous of each other, do come together.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſecond Argument ſhall be drawn <hi>from the ſhortneſs of the triumph of the Saints adverſaries.</hi> God will quickly cut aſunder the cords of the wicked, that plow upon <hi>Sions</hi> back, and make long their furrows. <hi>I have ſeen,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, the wicked in great power, and ſpreading himſelf like a green Bay tree; yet he paſſed away, and loe he was not, yea I ſought him, but he could not be found.</hi> His great power, which he abuſes to oppreſs and trouble, and himſelf too, ſhall quickly paſs away. All the glory of the ungodly is as a dream, and is chaſed away as a night viſion. And when they are laid in the duſt, and death is feeding on them, they can devour the upright no longer. And truly the more violent they are, the ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter oftentimes is their triumph; cruelty doth ripen them a pace for vengeance.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Third Argument ſhall be draw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from <hi>the ſhortneſs of the Saints continuance i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this vale of tears.</hi> Their tribulation cann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> poſſibly be of any long duration. The are but travellers through the world, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will quickly be at their journeyes en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:60678:52"/> A few years, nay perhaps a few months will bring them to eternity: and when time is no longer there will be no longer trouble. The thoughts of death, though terrible to the ungodly, as putting a full ſtop to all their conſolation, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing to the Saints. Death is their <hi>laſt Enemy;</hi> after death no enemy can moleſt them. Their dayes are ſwifter than a Weavers Shuttle; they haſt to an end, as the Ships of deſire to the Haven, or the Eagle to the prey: and as their dayes poſt away, ſo their troubles and diſtreſſes make ſpeed to a concluſion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A fourth Argument ſhall be drawn from the Saints immediate entrance into reſt upon their diſſolution. The Apoſtle joyns <hi>being diſſolved</hi> and <hi>being with Chriſt</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; and ſpeaking of believers in the general, he ſayes 2 <hi>Cor. 5. 1. For we know that if our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved, we have (not we ſhall have, but we have) a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens.</hi> The ſpirits of juſt men immediately upon their ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, are made perfect, perfectly free from ſin and miſery, which while united to the body they were loaded with.</p>
               <p>The Papiſts diſtinguiſh the Church into
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60678:53"/> 
                  <hi>Triumphantem in caelis, militantem in terra, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borantem in purgatorio,</hi> Triumphant in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Militant on Earth, Labouring in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory. The laſt member of the Diviſion, labouring in Purgatory, the Scripture no where mentions, but expreſs affirms the contrary, <hi>Rev. 14. 13. Bleſſed are the dead that dye in the Lord, from henceforth, yea ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their labours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Several miſerably deluded ſouls argue for perfection here; elſe ſay they how can the Saints be fitted for glory, if they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed all their dayes? It is eaſily anſwered, that the work of grace is carryed on all their life time, and at their diſſolution their ſouls are perfected. Death may be called a great change, not only in regard of the body, but in regard of the Soul too, becauſe the ſoul is perfectly purified, and ſin quite and clean aboliſhed. Neither let it ſeem abſurd that ſuch a change ſhould be; for if in the firſt moment of converſion there is an alteration or change from <hi>no grace</hi> to <hi>grace,</hi> ſurely 'tis not unreaſonable to think that at the moment of diſſolution, there ſhould be a change from <hi>imperfect grace</hi> to <hi>grace that is compleat.</hi> Thus the penitent Thiefs ſoul was perfected at his expiring, elſe he could not have been <hi>that day he dyed with Chriſt in Paradiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:60678:53"/>
               <p>It's plain that the Saints upon their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture hence do enter into reſt; therefore it muſt be granted, that their tribulation is but, as they are, ſhort liv'd; nay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they may outlive their tribulation, and behold a <hi>lightſome ever-tyde</hi> after a day of darkneſs and of gloomineſs. They may live to ſee the Goſpel in eſteem, after diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, and peace upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> after trouble.</p>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>USE I.</head>
                  <p>Is the tribulation of the Saints ſhort? <hi>then let not their faith fail;</hi> let it hold out a little longer, and its work will be at an end. Let faith but keep up the Ship but a little while longer in the ſtorm, and it will be ſafely landed. Leane a few dayes more upon the promiſes of ſupport and ſhelter, &amp; you will be paſt the pikes, and beyond all peril. When you are entred into the City of God, <hi>the door will be ſhut;</hi> and as you ſhall come out no more, ſo no evil ſhall enter after you, to moleſt or grieve you.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <head>USE II.</head>
                  <p>Is the tribulation of the Saints ſhort? <hi>then let not Patience grow weary.</hi> N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence indeed is a needful grace, but hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there will be no neceſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y or uſe of it, becauſe you ſhall never feel any more burthens. The benefit of affliction, and the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60678:54"/> nearneſs of your reſt, ſhould induce you to bear all with cheerfulneſs; <hi>When you ſee the end of the Lord,</hi> you will confeſs <hi>they are happy that endure,</hi> Jam. 5. 11.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="application">
                  <head>USE III.</head>
                  <p>Is the tribulation of the Saints ſhort? <hi>Then let their expectation be raiſed.</hi> Yet a little while, and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 37. Your Lord will be as an Hart, or young Roe upon the mountains of ſeparation; and when he comes, he will wipe away tears from all faces, and for all your affliction and tribulation, you ſhall have joy and triumph double, treble, nay ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times ten thouſand fold.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="application">
                  <head>USE IV.</head>
                  <p>Is the tribulations of the Saints ſhort? <hi>See the difference between the Saints and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi> The Saints ſufferings are like the ſinners eaſe and proſperity, both for a moment. Let not the world imagine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers miſerable; their miſery is no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then the worlds happineſs: And as the men of the world cannot be counted happy, becauſe their happineſs do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſo ſoon vaniſh; ſo neither can believers juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be eſteemed miſerable, becauſe their miſery is ſo tranſient. What is it to have
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:60678:54"/> tribulation for ten dayes, and then to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in the preſence of God, and of the Lamb for ever.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="doctrine">
               <head>The Seventh Doctrine.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whatſoever ſufferings he is expoſed to, a Chriſtian muſt be faithful.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>All the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble their father; of whom it is ſaid, that the Lord <hi>found his heart faithful before him,</hi> Neh. 9. 8. This charge in the text is ſtrict, <hi>Be thou faithful:</hi> And truly 'tis but needful, if theſe three things are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>A Chriſtians heart is treacherous,</hi> and apt to ſtart aſide like a deceitful bow A beſieged City, when the beſiegers, have friends w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thin the walls, that are ready to lay hold of any opportunity to betray it, the Inhabitants had need to be the more circumſpect and vigilant. Such a City is the embleme of a believer; though his heart be renewed, yet 'tis only in part, it remains ſtill in part corrupted, and that corruption ſides with the tempter, and is ready to yield and open to him. Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs therefore to the Lord, and to himſelf is often to be preſſed upon the Chriſtian.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:60678:55"/>2. <hi>Shaking temptations are likely to be met with,</hi> Mat. 7. 27. <hi>The rain will deſcend, and the floods come, and the winds blow and beat upon the houſe,</hi> to try whether it is founded on a Rock, or upon the ſand onely.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This charge to be faithful is very requiſite, if we conſider, that in time of ſhaking, <hi>many will take offence, and depart from Chriſt.</hi> Chriſtians in ſhew will then diſcover their want of faith, and love in truth: And when theſe fall off, the Saints had need to be cautioned. <hi>Do not you alſo leave me.</hi> That ſo they may reply with <hi>Peter,</hi> Joh. 6. 67, 68. <hi>Lord, to whom ſhall we go? Thou haſt the words of eternal life;</hi> and eternal life it ſelf to beſtow on us.</p>
               <p>In the further handling of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Firſt, I ſhall ſhew what it is to be faithful; Secondly, I ſhall give good and ſufficient reaſon, why a Chriſtian ſhould be faithful.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place, I am to ſhew <hi>what it is to be faithful.</hi> This Apoſtle does briefly, and yet excellently ſet forth, 1 <hi>Tim. 1. 18, 19. This charge I commit unto thee ſon</hi> Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy, <hi>according to the propheſies which went before on thee, that by them thou mighteſt war
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60678:55"/> a good warfare, holding Faith and a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> And in holding theſe, we hold all that is worth our care to ſecure.</p>
               <p>The Epithite <hi>Precious</hi> is given to Faith, 2 <hi>Pet. 1. 1. To them who have obtained the precious faith with us.</hi> And if you would know how precious, you have it, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 7. Faith is not only ſaid to be as precious as gold, but <hi>much more precious then gold,</hi> nay, <hi>much more precious then gold that periſheth,</hi> therefore 'tis to be held faſt.</p>
               <p>Now in holding of Faith theſe five things are implied. We hold faſt; firſt, <hi>the Doctrine,</hi> Secondly, <hi>the Object.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>the Confidence.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>the Life.</hi> Fifthly, <hi>the Profeſſion</hi> of our faith without waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He that is faithful, <hi>holds faſt the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of faith.</hi> The truthes of Chriſt he looks upon as worth the buying at any rate: but nothing ſhall make him ſell them. <hi>Buy the truth, and ſell it not,</hi> ſaid wiſe <hi>Solomon.</hi> Truth is of God; a bright and glorious beam, that ſhines from the Sun of righteouſneſs. Truth is a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Pilot, his Compaſs; he will quickly ſplit on ſome rock, or ſink in ſome ſand; if this be not heeded the Chriſtian is in a
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60678:56"/> dark place, where ſtumbling blocks and ſnares are innumerable many: and the truth of Chriſt, the doctrine of faith is a light unto his feet, and a lamp unto his paths.</p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>Pergamus</hi> though they welt where Satans ſeat was, yet ſayes Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 13. Thou holdeſt faſt my name, <hi>and haſt not decayed my Faith;</hi> that is, <hi>my doctrine,</hi> which I delivered to be believed and obeyed. Rather then the Goſpel ſhould be let go, and buried in ſilence, we muſt venture all for its propagation. Even <hi>Peace it ſelf,</hi> we are to endeavour after no further then conſiſtent with truth. The Apoſtle matter'd not what troubles and ſtir the Goſpel occaſioned, and though Satan and the ungodly did ſtorm at the light, they boldly did publiſh that meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage which they had a command to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. As long as the Goſpel lives and thrives; no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what diſturbances are created by its enemies.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He that is faithful <hi>holds faſt the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Faith.</hi> Now the Object of faith is ſaid down; <hi>Joh. 14. 1. Ye believe in God, believe alſo in me,</hi> ſayes Chriſt to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. 'Tis our duty, and our ſafety to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60678:56"/> cleave unto the onely true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent. A believer keeps his hold of God, who is his ſhield, and exceeding great reward; who can defend him from evil, or turn thoſe evils which he feels, to his advantage, who can crown him with loving kindneſs, and ſuch mercies as are tender, ſutable, ſatisfactory and ſure. Neither will he let go his hold of Jeſus Chriſt who brought him near, and keeps him near unto this God, who guides him by his ſpirit, who by vertue of his blood and interceſſion, is continually making up the breaches that the believers ſinful infirmities do make; and who out of his fulneſs is ready to impart whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver grace in any time of need is neceſſary. 3. He that is faithful <hi>holds faſt his aſſurance and confidence of faith.</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter he hath given all diligence to attain aſſurance, he is loth to loſe what coſt him ſuch pains to get. The Apoſtle pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſes this again and again, <hi>Heb. 3. 6. But Chriſt as a ſon over his own houſe, whoſe houſe we are,</hi> if we hold faſt the confidence <hi>and rejoycing of hope firm unto the end.</hi> And Heb. 10. 5. <hi>Caſt not away therefore your confidence which hath great recompence of reward.</hi> Aſſurance of faith is a mighty ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in the evil day. The eye of faith when
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60678:57"/> faith is heightned into a full perſwaſion and confidence, will look through the clouds, and behold God ſmiling when men do frown: faith will hear God ſpeaking peace in a ſtill voyce, when the mouths of men are full of threatnings and furious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes: Faith will perceive the better ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance enduring, when earthly goods are taken away,</p>
               <p>But when troubles on earth ſurround us on every ſide, and we are at uncertainties what will be our lot in the next world: When there are <hi>fightings without,</hi> and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to our ſpiritual eſtate, <hi>doubts and fears within;</hi> this will render our condition dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Oh therefore labour and pray for aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, cheriſh not any diſtemper of heart, give no place to the Devil, for thus doing will feed your fears, and ſtrengthen your unbelief.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He that is faithful <hi>holds faſt the life of faith.</hi> As this is the ſafeſt, ſo 'tis the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt life on earth. They that walk by ſight and not by faith, will preſently grow faint and weary in the hour of temptation. If fleſh and blood are conſulted with, if our murmuring and repining ſenſes are heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, we ſhall refuſe to rowe againſt the ſtream, and be carryed away with the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60678:57"/> of the times we live in. If <hi>Moſes</hi> had been led by ſenſe, his choice and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice would have been contrary to what it was. Senſe would have prized Honour, and ſo he would <hi>have ſtill been called the Son of Pharaohs Daughter.</hi> Senſe would have coveted wealth and delight, and ſo he would have had his heart glewed <hi>to the pleaſures of ſin,</hi> and <hi>the treaſures of Egypt.</hi> But <hi>Moſes</hi> walked by faith, and therefore choſe to ſuffer afflictions with the people of God, he eſteemed it part of his riches to be reproached for Chriſt, for faith conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually ſhewed <hi>Him that is inviſible</hi> and <hi>the Recompence of reward</hi> to him, Heb. 11. 24, 25, 26, 27.</p>
               <p>So the Apoſtle walked by faith, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth <hi>Gal. 2. 20. I am crucified with Chriſt, nevertheleſs, I live; yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me; and the life which I now live in the fleſh, I live by the faith of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himſelf for me.</hi> They that live by faith ſtay themſelves upon the promiſes of ſuſtentation, and no weight can<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſink them: they c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt their burthens and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too upon the Lord, who being faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful will not ſuffer them to be tempted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove what they are able.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He that is faithful <hi>holds faſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60678:58"/> of his faith.</hi> He heeds that admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb. 10. 25. Let us hold faſt the profeſſion of our faith without wavering, for he is faithful that hath promiſed.</hi> He is not aſham'd of his Lord &amp; Maſter, nay eſteems it an honour for his Maſters ſake to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed. Though the Kings and Rulers of the earth take counſel, and ſet themſelves againſt the Lords Chriſt, yet the faithfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſervant will ſtick to him. He is not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be of that way <hi>that is every wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſpoken againſt;</hi> He is not aſhamed of that Goſpel, which is <hi>a ſtumbling block to the Jewes, to the Greeks fooliſhneſs;</hi> he is not aſhamed of that word which <hi>a ſinful and adulterous Generation reproach, and have no delight in it,</hi> Jer. 6. 10.</p>
               <p>His principal care and ſtudy indeed is to be a ſincere lover, and real practiſer of Religion; and yet he is not afraid to be an open profeſſour, though thereby it comes to paſs that he is evil entreated by religious enemies. That's the firſt thing implyed in being faithful, namely <hi>Holding Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. To be faithful is alſo <hi>to hold a good conſcience.</hi> When <hi>Paul</hi> ſtood before the Council, earneſtly beholding them he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, <hi>I have lived in all good conſcience before
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60678:58"/> God unto this day,</hi> Acts 23. 1. So Acts 24. 16. Herein do I exerciſe my ſelf, to have a conſcience void of offence towards God and towards men. The unſtedfaſt profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour regards not his conſcience, makes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of wounding and defiling it. But the faithful ſoul ſpeaks much what the ſame language with holy <hi>Job,</hi> chap. 27. 5, 6. <hi>Till I dye I will not remove my integrity from me; my righteouſneſs I hold faſt, and will not let it go, my heart ſhall not reproach me ſo long as I live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are theſe three things that argue a good conſcience.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Where the conſcience is good, <hi>no ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful deſigns are carryed on.</hi> Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſter aimes are not allowed by one that is faithful. If his treacherous heart begin to have a ſquin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eye at his own praiſe or profit, he checks it preſently. What he <hi>doth,</hi> he deſigns that God may have the glory of; and ſurely the glory is the Lords due, ſince his ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening grace doth <hi>all in us, and for us.</hi> And by <hi>ſuffering,</hi> the faithful man aimes not at the advancing his own repute, but that Chriſt may be magnified by his tryals, his patience and joy in them. And if the world be convinced, the weak confirmed, if the Goſpel get ground, and the Lord Jeſus be
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60678:59"/> by a greater multitude prized and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he hath his end.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Where the conſcience is good, <hi>ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſires are not harbour'd.</hi> He that is faithful looks well to his deſires, that they be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved pure. The World is undeſirable, ſin is abominable, but <hi>his ſoul thirſteth for God, for the living God,</hi> Pſal. 42. 2. and ſufferings are willingly undergone, ſo this thirſt may be ſatisfied.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Where conſcience is good, 'tis <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from dead works,</hi> Heb. 9. 14. <hi>How much more ſhall the blood of Chriſt, who through the eternal Spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffered himſelf without ſpot to God, purge your conſciences from dead works to ſerve the living God?</hi> A good conſcience will not wink at unwarrantable practiſes, will not connive at not doing the work of the Lord, or doing that work negligently. He that is faithful makes conſcience to walk before God in truth, though never ſo many in their works deny the Lord: he is grieved and vexed at others filthy converſation, and orders his own aright; and ſo though for a while he is uſed hardly, <hi>he comes at length to ſee the ſalvation of God,</hi> Pſal. 50. ult.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond place I am to lay down the Reaſons why a Chriſtian ſhould be faithful.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:60678:59"/>1. <hi>A Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ian is under a command to be faithful.</hi> And this command to be ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, is very expreſſive, 'tis very much pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſed in Scripture, 1 Cor. 15. 58. <hi>Be ſtedfaſt, unmovable, alwayes abounding in the work of the Lord.</hi> Phil. 4. 1. <hi>So ſtand faſt in the Lord my dearly beloved.</hi> 1 Cor. 16. 13. <hi>Watch ye ſtand faſt in the faith, quit ye like men.</hi> Joh. 8. 31. <hi>Jeſus ſaid unto them that believed on him; if ye continue in my word, then are ye my Diſciples indeed. Moſes</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of old, did harp upon this ſtring; commanding the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> not only to turn, but to cleave unto the Lord, Deut. 30. 20. <hi>That thou mayeſt love the Lord thy God, and obey his voice, and cleave unto him, for he is thy life.</hi> And they are forbid to turn either to the right hand, or the left from following the Lord their God. Now all theſe commands make the Chriſtians obligation to faithfulneſs the ſtronger: and truly to be unfaithful is not a ſingle ſin, for he that leaves the Lord, how fearfully muſt he be drawn into tranſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greſſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>A Chriſtian is under covenant to he faithful.</hi> Deut. 26. 17. He has avouched the Lord to be his God. He was given up to God betimes, and how often has he made of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60678:60"/> himſelf a freſh reſignation, upon dayes of humiliation? and when he has eat and drunk at the Lords table, his covenant to be the Lords has been renewed. How often has the Chriſtian profeſſed, that his heart and members were not his own but Gods, to dwell in, and to make uſe of: this is another reaſon, and a ſtrong one why he ſhould be faithful. The Lord is the Chriſtians, and the Chriſtian is the Lords portion. <hi>The Lords portion is his people, and Jacob is the lot of his inheritance.</hi> Now Gods inheritance ſhould be for his uſe, and ſhould in no wiſe be alienated.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The God of believers is faithful, therefore they ſhall reſemble him.</hi> The Scripture ſpeaks in a glorious ſtrain concerning the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of God. He is ſaid to keep truth for ever. The hills and mountains ſtand not ſo firm as his covenant ſhall. <hi>Lev. 54. 10. For the mountains ſhall depart, and the hills be removed, but my kindneſs ſhall not depart from thee, nor the covenant of my peace be removed, ſaith the Lord that hath mercy on thee.</hi> Nay the Scripture goes much higher then the Mountains, in ſetting forth this faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>I have ſaid, mercy ſhall be built up for ever; Thy faithfulneſs ſhalt thou eſtabliſh in the very Heavens.</hi> And being thus eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60678:60"/> nothing on earth can ſhake their faithfulneſs, 'twill be as apparent and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious as the Heavens are: The Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Heaven, as the Sun by day, and of the Moon and Stars by night, are not more unalterable than the Lords Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 33, 34, 35, 36.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The Lord is glorified by a Chriſtians prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faithful.</hi> It reflects diſhonour upon him when his Servants leave him. Oh then how faithful ſhould they be? The worlds prejudices againſt the Lords ſervice are heightned, and they are hardned in their ſtubborn and evil way, when they behold profeſſours apoſtatize, and become again their companions in the paths of folly and wickedneſs. But the faithful man cauſes the way of truth to be well ſpoken of; by his faithfulneſs he proclaims his Maſters <hi>goodneſs</hi> and his <hi>power,</hi> and both wayes is his Maſter glorified.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>He proclaims his Maſters goodneſs,</hi> and that he hath made the beſt choyce, ſince he will ſuffer any thing rather than part with his Lord. The <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> ſervant that refuſed to go out free at the year of releaſe, and had his ear boared through with an Awl, 'twas a plain demonſtration of his Maſters kindneſs, ſince liberty was not ſo
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60678:61"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch eſteemed as his ſervice. And ſo when we are unmovable in our Lords work, we tell the World that our Maſter is exceeding gracious; and who knows but that by this means the number of his ſervants may be increaſed?</p>
               <p n="2">2. The man that's faithful <hi>proclaims his Lords power.</hi> The power of Chriſt doth reſt upon him, elſe he would be unſtable as water, who through Chriſt ſtrengthening of him is like the very Rock unſhaken; and the more weak the Believer is, the more glorious is his power in whom he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves.</p>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>USE I.</head>
                  <p>Of Reproof, and I ſhall direct it to two ſorts of perſons.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>The fickle and unconſtant are to be reprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Their ſpirit is unſtedfaſt with the Lord, if the World make proffer of its good things, or threaten them with evil. Vain hopes draw them away, vain fears drive them away from Chriſt. Somtimes they ſeem to be <hi>his humble Servants;</hi> but this is only an hypocritical kind of complement; Self they are reſolved to ſerve, to pleaſe, and to ſecure, whatever become of Chriſt, his Honour, and his Goſpel.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>They are to be reproved that are in an ill
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60678:61"/> ſenſe faithful;</hi> Faithful to their ſins, which are the worſt maſters; unmoveable in their reſolution to make proviſion for the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh, to fulfil the luſts thereof. There is a ſtrange ſtou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neſs of ſpirit, and fixed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in evil, that is to be found in thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands: <hi>Their neck is like an iron ſinew, their brow like braſs; they make their faces harder then a rock, they refuſe to return.</hi> Say what we will, ſin is their maſter, and ſin they will ſerve, though they be told an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and an hundred times that <hi>death is its wages.</hi> They a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e as unchangeable in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil as the ſpots of the Leopard, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or the blackneſs of the Ethiopian. Oh that we would learn of ſins vaſſals, to be as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the beſt, as they are to the worſt Lord.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <head>USE II.</head>
                  <p>Of Exhortation. Let me preſs you to be faithful.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>How many obligations lye upon you to be ſtedfaſt?</hi> infinite millions of encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he gives you: the more conſtant, the more comfort and peace is found. <hi>Great peace have they, ſayes David, that love thy law, and nothing ſhall offend them.</hi> Every mercy of thoſe many thouſands you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, ſhould be a cord to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ye you faſter
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:60678:62"/> unto God; and what ſtrange kind of hearts have you, if ſo many cords are ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>apt aſunder, and ſo many obligations are forgotten.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Whom do you leave when you are unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful?</hi> you forſake that Lord whoſe loving kindneſs is ſo excellent, who is able to perform all things for you, whoſe all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency can furniſh you though never ſo indigent. This God you leave, and for what do you leave him? 'Tis for that which is not bread? 'Tis for that <hi>which can never ſatisfie, Iſa.</hi> 55. 2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By unfaithfulneſs you not only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive your ſelves of the Lords goodneſs, <hi>but engage him againſt you,</hi> Ezra 8. 22. <hi>His hand is upon all them for good that ſeek him, but his power and his wrath is againſt thoſe that forſake him.</hi> And wrath armed with ſuch power is dreadful. God greatly abhors the backſlider: when his ancient people <hi>turned back, and dealt unfaithfully like their fathers,</hi> 'tis ſaid, <hi>When the Lord heard this he was wroth, and greatly abhorred Iſrael,</hi> Pſal. 78. 57, 59.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>If you are faithful with God, you ſhall find by experience his wayes to be truth and mercy,</hi> Pſal. 25. 10. <hi>All the paths of the Lord are mercy and truth, unto ſuch as keep
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60678:62" rendition="simple:additions"/> his covenant and his teſtimonies.</hi> His promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes you ſhall experience to be true; his mercies will all <hi>in mercy</hi> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>oved; Nay there will be mercy in every affliction, in every diſtreſs, mercy ſupporting, mercy reviving, mercy turning all things to the beſt: As the Philoſophers ſtone is ſaid to turn all me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tals into gold.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="application">
                  <head>USE III.</head>
                  <p>Of direction how to be made faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Be ſenſible of the treachery of your own ſpirits,</hi> and let this make you the more jealous of your ſelves all your dayes. <hi>Watch ye, ſtand faſt,</hi> ſayes the Apoſtle. If you would ſtand faſt you muſt be exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vigilant. Watch that nothing come in at the door of your ſenſes, which may prove a ſnare; and that nothing go out of your heart which may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file you. When firſt the heart begins to grow weary of well-doing, or to hearken to the tempter, obſerve it, and being apprehenſive of your dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, cry to be quickned and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Pray to be upheld by the ſpirit of the Lord.</hi> Thus did <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 51. 12.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60678:63"/> Reſtore unto me the joy of thy ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and uphold me with thy free ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Where the ſpirit of the Lord is, there is liberty, life, holineſs, ſtrength. Grieve not the ſpirit, but be obſequious to him, and he will ſtrengthen you with might in your inward man. When Chriſt was about to go away, and part with his Diſciples, he promiſes to ſend the ſpirit who ſhould abide with them for ever; and 'twas by this ſpirit that they were born up and carried thorow all their work, and the difficulties that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Plead the Covenant,</hi> one clauſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is this; <hi>I will not turn away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>from them to do them good, and I will put my fear into their hearts that they ſhall not depart from me,</hi> Jer. 32. 40. Again he ſaith, Jer. 3. 19. <hi>Thou ſhalt call me my Father, and ſhalt not depart from me.</hi> Prize theſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, plead them, believe them, and as ſure as God is faithful, he <hi>will make you faithful whatever your ſufferings or temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="doctrine">
               <head>The Eighth Doctrine.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Chriſtians faithfulneſs muſt run parallel with his life, to the death he muſt be ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:60678:63"/>
               <p>This <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to the death,</hi> may have a double interpretation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Be thou faithful to the death, that is, <hi>be thou unmovable, though it coſt thee thy life to be ſo.</hi> Prefer not thy life before that Lord who laid down his life to redeem thee from death, and who will recompence the loſs of life temporal with that life that's ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. <hi>A Chriſtian is to reſiſt even unto blood, ſtriving againſt ſin,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks; he muſt chooſe rather to part with his blood, than to loſe his God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Be faithful to the death, that is, <hi>all thy dayes be faithful;</hi> that when death comes, and the Lord by death, he may find thee doing his work, doubling his talents, ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up for his intereſt, notw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thſtanding all deriſion and oppoſition.</p>
               <p>The Reaſons why we ſhould be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the death are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Much of the former part of our life hath been loſt; therefore all the remainder ſhould be the more faithfully devoted to God.</hi> The time paſt of our life may more than ſuffice to have diſhonoured him; therefore all the <hi>reſt of our time in the fleſh, ſhould be lived, not to the luſts of men</hi> (either our own luſts, or the luſts of others) <hi>but to the will of God,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 2, 3. The whole was his due, let
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:60678:64"/> him not be denyed that part which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The longer we know our Lord, and the cloſer we keep to him, the better we ſhall like him;</hi> therefore 'tis but reaſon that to the laſt we ſhould be ſtedfaſt. <hi>Cardinal Wolſey</hi> indeed was weary of the ſervice of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, and ſaid, <hi>If he had ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God ſo faithfully as he had done the King, God would not have forſaken him in his gray hairs.</hi> But Chriſt is another kind of Maſter than any other Potentate. <hi>Old Polycarpus</hi> ſaid, <hi>he had ſerved Chriſt for ſeveral Scores of years, and knew nothing but good by him,</hi> and therefore in his old age he choſe to ſuffer any thing rather than deny him. The harder we follow after Chriſt, and the longer we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his diſciples, we diſcover new beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, new pleaſures, new treaſures, and ſo we can never find juſt reaſon to exchange, ſince 'twill be ſo much for the worſe; but juſt reaſon to the contrary, ſince Chriſts lovlineſs, and fulneſs, and libetality in communicating of that fulneſs, doth daily more and more abundantly appear.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>If we are not faithful to the death, all that we have done before will be loſt;</hi> we ſhall loſe thoſe things which we have wrought, and miſs of our reward. That's a full place,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:60678:64"/> 
                  <hi>Ezek. 18. 24. But when the righteous man turneth away from his righteouſneſs, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth iniquity, and doth according to all the ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations that the wicked man doth, ſhall he live? All his righteouſneſs that he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>one ſhall not be mentioned; in his treſpaſs that he hath treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed, and in his ſin which he hath ſinned, in them ſhall he dye.</hi> By the righteous man we are to underſtand one that by profeſſion is righteous, and outwardly unblamable, performing the duties required of him; if he give out and turn aſide, all his duties will be loſt, all his hearing, all his prayers, all his deeds of juſtice and mercy will not be mention'd; he continues not ſtedfaſt, which ſhews he was never ſincere, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever others were deceived in him, and himſelf too.</p>
               <div type="application">
                  <head>USE.</head>
                  <p>The only Uſe of this Doctrine ſhall be <hi>to admoniſh all that profeſs the name of Chriſt, to perſevere to the end.</hi> Depart from iniquity, but never from your Lord. When firſt you give up your ſelves to Chriſt, reckon upon this, that you muſt ever abide with him. Your cloſing with Chriſt is a marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and this Husband never dies, you muſt not give away your ſelves to another. The Arguments to perſwade you to be faithful till death are theſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:60678:65"/>1. <hi>Many unfaithful ones at death tremble and are in horrour becauſe of their Apoſtacy.</hi> Conſcience often awakes when the King of terrours is within view: a dreadful ſound is in the backſliders ears, trouble and anguiſh make him afraid and prevail againſt him, as a King ready to the Battel. To have ones ſpirit wounded with an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> tollerable ſtroke, to have the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vils accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, the creatures all failing, ſins ſet in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der before the eyes, calamity as a ſtorm ready to hur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> one out of the would, and God ſo far from pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ving as to laugh at ones deſtruction, and <hi>to be comforted in the vengeance that is inflicted.</hi> Ezek. 5. 13. muſt needs be very dreadful: But this is the dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful caſe &amp; concluſion of many ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ders.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Death is near at hand, think net much of ſo ſhort a time to be faithful.</hi> If a Maſter ſhould ſay, <hi>Work hard to day, and I will give thee an inheritance for thy life,</hi> verily the moſt ſlothful would not think much of the heat and burthen. Now God ſayes, abide in my ſervice for a little while, and then you ſhall reſt from all your labours and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and that reſt ſhall be for ever. Oh how ſhould this encourage!</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Faithfulneſs to the death will take away the fear of death.</hi> Death will be look upon
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60678:65"/> a Meſſenger to tell you that your Lord can no longer brook your abſence, to tell you that your warfare is accompliſhed; and that having been faithful in your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters buſineſs you muſt enter into your Maſters joy. Be but faithful unto death, and Chriſt will ſtand by you at death; and after death he will receive you.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="doctrine">
               <head>The Ninth Doctrine.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon thoſe that continue faithful unto death, Chriſt will certainly beſtow a Crown of Life and Immortality <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>If the eye of Faith were but more open and ſtrong-ſighted, how would this Crown gliſter and ſhine? What a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment inducement would it prove to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance?</p>
               <p>In the handling of this Doctrine, I ſhall firſt endeavour to ſhew, what, and what manner of life the text ſpeakes of. Secondly, in what regard this life is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Crown. Thirdly, lay down ſome arguments to prove the certainty of the certainty of the doctrine, that the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſhall be thus crown'd with immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, then cloſe with the uſes.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place I am to ſhew what, and what manner of life the text ſpeakes of. A ſubject I confeſs, more fit for an
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60678:66"/> Angels tongue then mine. The ſoul while impriſoned in the body is of a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row capacity; and apprehends but little of that glory which is above. The actual inhabitants of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> can b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t tell what kinde of habitation it is. They that are but paſſing through the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this world, know but little what manner of life is lead in the heavenly <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nnaan;</hi> yet ſince we have a Map of this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed land of promiſe, in the word: let us take a view of it, and let us view ſo long, till we cry with <hi>Auguſtines</hi> mother, <hi>Quid hic facimus?</hi> What do we here? and groan with pangs of deſire to be gone from hence and poſſeſſed of our heavenly country. Now what the word ſpeaks of <hi>this life above,</hi> in theſe particulars I ſhall declare.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That life above, <hi>will conſiſt in the neareſt union and conjunction to God.</hi> Life natural is the reſult of union between the ſoul and body: and life eternal, of the union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſoul and God. And truly to be baniſhed and ſeparated from the Lord for ever, will be the ſecond death. The Apoſtle comforts the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> with this, Chap. 4. Epiſt. 2. v. 17. <hi>So ſhall we ever be with the Lord.</hi> How near their God will the Saints be admitted hereafter? His
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:60678:66" rendition="simple:additions"/> dwelling in them is comparatively called an <hi>Abſence,</hi> in reſpect of that preſence in the other world to be vouchſafed. Theſe three things will be conſequent upon this union to God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>One will be the viſion or ſeeing of God,</hi> ſayes the Apoſtle, 1 Cor. 13. 12. <hi>For now we ſee through a glaſs darkly; but then face to face: now I know in part, but then I ſhall know even as alſo I am known.</hi> The Saints ſhall no longer complain of darkneſs, of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, of thoſe <hi>horribiles dubitationes</hi> as <hi>Melancthon</hi> calls them, horrible doubtings concerning God, with which they are ſometimes haunted. They ſhall ſee God immediately, and what they behold how will it raiſe their love, and joy, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der! The Lord ſaid to <hi>Moſes, Thou canſt not ſee my face and live,</hi> q. d. Such a ſight would be ſo glorious as that thy fraile nature would be overwhelmed by it. But the perfected Saints are ſtrengthened for ſuch a felicity, their life lies in looking and gazing at him; whoſe glory ſhould it but ſhine forth, would overwhelm the moſt ſanctified mortal here on earth.</p>
               <p>And when the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of God is ſeen, the ſoul is <hi>all light, all love.</hi> All the excellencies and beauties in the creatures whereby af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is attracted, in compariſon of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60678:67"/> what is to be ſeen in God, are not ſo much as the thouſandth part of the leaſt ſpark of fire, compared with the Sun when it ſhines in its greateſt ſtrength and noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide glory. The face of God will then be ſmooth, not one frown to be ſeen, not one look that will manifeſt the leaſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure. Nothing but ſmiles and glorious aſpects, which will evidently ſhew the incomprehenſible greatneſs of his love unto, and joy that he takes in, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly purified veſſels of glory.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another conſequent of this union to God <hi>will be likeneſs to him. But as for me,</hi> ſayes David, <hi>I will behold thy face in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; I ſhall be ſatisfied when I awake with thy likeneſs,</hi> Pſal. 17. 15. The ſight of God will be transforming, and that like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will cauſe abundant ſatisfaction. The beholding of the Lord in his ordinances, does in a degree, <hi>change us into the ſame image from glory to glory,</hi> 2 Cor. 3. ult. and much more the beholding of him in his kingdom, 1 <hi>Joh. 3. 2. Beloved, now are we the ſons of God, and it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be, but we know, that when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> Then the Image of God begun here will be compleated. Here 'tis but like a rude draught, like a picture in
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60678:67" rendition="simple:additions"/> dead colours; but then the piece will have had Gods laſt hand upon it, the work will be finiſhed; and Oh how exactly like will all the children be to their holy and heavenly Father? Now they hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſs; but then the promiſe of filling them will be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled and performed to the uttermoſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Another conſequent of this union to God, <hi>will be the full enjoyment of him.</hi> The Saints pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t after the Lord now, as the chaſed Hart after the water-brooks; but in glory they ſhall have as much of God as they can deſire, or contain, The holy Ghoſt tells us that God <hi>will be all in all;</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 28. All that they can wiſh, all ſufficient to fill them to the brim. The goodneſs, and power, and faithfulneſs, and love of God, have ſometimes deep and ſweet impreſſions on the Saints <hi>now:</hi> But whot will the impreſſions <hi>then</hi> be? how durable, how tranſporting? they ſhall lye as it were, with their heads at the fountain of living waters perpetually; no thirſt, no ſcantineſs will be complained of. Theſe are the conſequents of that near union and communion to God, wherein this life above will conſiſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That life above will <hi>be moſt holy and unſpotted.</hi> Sin will be pardoned, and quite
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60678:68"/> and clean aboliſhed. <hi>Filia dev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rabit Matrem,</hi> Death the daughter will put an end to ſin the mother. Believers though alive by grace, do carry a body of death about with them, which makes the condition ſomewhat like theirs who f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll into the hands of the Tyrant of old called <hi>Mezen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins,</hi> who
<q>
                     <p>—<hi>Mortua jungebat corpora vivis Componen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> manibuſque manus, atq, oribus ora.</hi> Virg.</p>
                  </q> joyned the members of a living man to a dead carkaſs, the hands, and breaſt, and face of the one, to thoſe of the other. But when the Saints are come to glory, the body of death will be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>illed, though the natural body will be raiſed, yet the body of ſin will never have a reſurrection. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of, <hi>Oh wretched! who ſhall deliver us?</hi> will be, <hi>glory and everlaſting praiſe to him who hath made us free from ſin, the worſt of evils, and from all the leſſer miſeries that attend it!</hi> The Spouſe of Chriſt <hi>will then be preſented a glorious Church, not having ſpot, or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing: but 'twill be holy and without blemiſh,</hi> Eph. 5. 27. Then the blood of Chriſt will have had its perfect operation. The Saints will be waſhed white as Snow, they will look as white, or whiter then <hi>Adam</hi> did in innocency. All ſpots will be
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:60678:68" rendition="simple:additions"/> done off. Every wrinkle wil be ſmoothed, and the members every one of them, like their head; <hi>altogether lovely.</hi> The Church is <hi>now fair as the Moon,</hi> ſpots it hath with its fairneſs, ſometimes it waxes, ſometimes it wanes; but when 'tis tranſlated to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven 'twill be clear as the Sun it ſelf, Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6. 10.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That life above will <hi>be moſt ſweet and pleaſant.</hi> The Saints ſhall no longer cry out vanity and vexation of ſpirit; as they did when under the Sun. <hi>But God will wipe away all tears from their eyes, and there ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow nor crying, neither ſhall there be any more pain, for the former things be paſt away. Rev.</hi> 21. 4. When they come to live in the preſence of God; their Joy will be ſo full, as to be un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> able of any addition, when they are at Gods right hand, their pleaſures will be for ever. Even in this vail of tears there is a peace attended which paſſes all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, a joy that is unſpeakable and full of glory. So that the Saints mouthes are ſongs in the houſe of their pilgrimage. Oh then how ſhort and unſuitable are out apprehenſions of the pleaſures dealt forth in the heavenly paradiſe!</p>
               <p n="4">4. That life above will <hi>be moſt ſecure and ſafe.</hi> Dangers will then be all gone thorow.
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:60678:69"/> When we are entring into the gate of the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> we ſhall ſhake hands with all the enemies that before moleſted us, and not ſo much as one of them will be able to follow us. The great gulph be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and them, will keep them off at an everlaſting diſtance. There will be no danger, either from within, or from without. No ſerpent in that para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe to tempt man again to fall from his reſtored innocency. The heart will confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in goodneſs, 'twil never have the leaſt inclination to decline from God: There will be no need of that vigilancy and ſtanding upon our guard, that now is neceſſary; for our hearts will be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cured of their deceitfulneſs, and there will be no adverſaries to lay ſnares for us.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That life above <hi>will be moſt quiet and peaceable.</hi> 'Tis not improbable that in the latter dayes there will be a more peaceable Church ſtate, than as yet there hath been; when that promiſe, and others of the like nature, will be more viſibly accompliſhed, <hi>Iſa. 11. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. The Branch of Jeſſe with righteouſneſs ſhall judge the poor, and reprove with equity for the meek of the earth: he ſhall ſmite the earth with the Rod of his mouth, and with the breath of his lips ſhall he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; and righteouſneſs ſhall be the girdle of his
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:60678:69"/> loyns, and faithfulneſs the girdle of his reins. The Wolf alſo ſhall dwell with the Lamb, and the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard ſhall lye down with the Kid; and the Calf, and the young Lion, and the Fatling together, &amp; a little Child ſhall lead them. And the ſucking Child ſhall play on the hole of the Aſp, and the weaned Child ſhall put his hand on the Cockatrice Den: They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy Mountain.</hi> But moſt certainly this peace and concord ſhall be among the Saints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove; no biting, no devouring one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, no diverſity of judgments, but all will agree in the ſame truth; no alienati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of affection, for love to the Lord, and to one another will be perfect; the ſpirit that luſteth to envy will be caſt out, ſelfiſh ends will carry none aſide, diſputes will be at an end, the wounds which diviſions have made will be cloſed. How good and pleaſant will be that unity, when all the Saints will be of one, &amp; of the right mind.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The life above <hi>will be lead among the moſt ſuitable ſociety.</hi> The Saints will then have bid farewel to <hi>Meſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ech</hi> and the Tents of <hi>Kedar;</hi> they ſhall no longer dwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong revilers at holineſs, the openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, the ſcandalous or lifeleſs profeſſors of Religion; no filthy communication or converſation in heaven to vex their righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſouls; no contempt of God, no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:60678:70"/> the eyes of his glory; no curſing, ſwearing, pride, wantonneſs, to be heard or ſeen in the heavenly City. When they come thither, they will ſay, <hi>How bleſſedly unlike is this, to that place and company which we came from.</hi> Glorified ſpirits, innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble companies of Angels will be their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, theſe will be glad to ſee them ſafely arrived unto reſt: For if there be joy in heaven at the converſion of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, we may very well infer, there will be joy likewiſe at the Saints Coronation.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That life above <hi>will fully anſwer its end.</hi> The Saints were formed by the Lord for himſelf, and they will be eternally ſhewing forth his praiſe and glory. They will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver entertain ſo much as an unbecoming thought of God; but to magnifie and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tol him will be their everlaſting buſineſs; their hearts and their Harpes will be ever in tune to ſound forth his Name. Now they do but liſp and ſtammer out his prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; but then how ſeraphical will their Songs be? and they will never be weary of ſinging <hi>Hallelujahs.</hi> Oh what extaſies of joy and love; with what raviſhment of ſpirit, with what unconceivable raptures of delight, will the whole Aſſembly and Church of the Firſt-born joyn together, ſaying, <hi>Amen, bleſſing, and glory, and wiſdome,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:60678:70"/> and thanksgiving, and honour, and power, and might be unto our God for ever and ever, Amen,</hi> Rev. 7. 12. The triumphant Saints will perfectly anſwer the deſign of God, in their Creation, in their new Creation; they will glorifie him for ever, who upon them hath beſtowed eternal Glory.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The life above <hi>will be an everlaſting life.</hi> Death it ſelf will be deſtroyed and ſwallowed up in victory. The eternity of the Saints joyes and enjoyments, makes them infinitely of the greater value. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven would be no longer Heaven, were they ever to be turned out of it; all the ſweetneſs would be imbittered with the thoughts of its period. But adored be the riches of mercy, the inheritance is ſaid to be <hi>incorruptible,</hi> the Kingdome <hi>cannot be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> the Crown of glory <hi>fadeth not away; the gift of God is eternal life, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> Rom. 6. ult.</p>
               <p>How<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ye damned ſpirits, your miſeries are everlaſting, you are baniſhed from God, and ſhall never be called back; but be unconſumed fewel for unquench able flames. Triumph and r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yce ye glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Souls: As long as God <hi>is,</hi> he will be <hi>your</hi> God, your portion, your reward; as long as God is, you ſhall live in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and enjoy him. Thus you ſee what<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:60678:71"/> &amp; what manner of life the Text ſpeaks of.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond place I am to ſhew upon what ſcore this Life is called a Crown.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This Crown intimates <hi>that the Saints are Conquerours.</hi> They have run the Race, and won the prize; they have fought the good fight of Faith, and laid hold on eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life. They may truly ſay <hi>ſuper-ſuperamus,</hi> we are more than conquerours. They have, being ſtrengthned by him that loveth them, conquered the whole World, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered the Principallities and Powers of Hell, conquered themſelves too, their own luſts, and paſſions, and affections. All other Battels are but petty skirmiſhes to the ſpiritual combate; mortal men are but inconſiderable enemies compared with fleſhly luſts and evil Angels. All the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours recorded in Hiſtory are hardly worth the mentioning with a Chriſtian that endures and overcomes. And what is Lawrel to that Crown at laſt put upon the Chriſtians Head?</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Crown ſpeaks <hi>the honour and dignity whereunto the Saints are advanced.</hi> Though exceedingly filled with contempt and the ſcorning of thoſe that are at eaſe, yet even here the Saints are <hi>Kings &amp; Prieſts,</hi> Rev. 1. 5, 6. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto him that loved us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood, and hath
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:60678:71"/> made us Kings and Prieſts unto God and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; to him be Glory and Dominion for ever and ever.</hi> And when they come to Glory they are actually crown'd; then 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent the World was not worthy of them, and that far better than what the world could beſtow, is freely given them. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is called a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> the Reward a <hi>Crown,</hi> to ſhew 'tis no mean prize the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian aimes at. What is all the height and grandeur on earth to the Kingly dignity put upon believers? What are all the Kingdomes of the world, and the glory of them, to reigning with the Lord for ever? The four great Monarchies by the Holy Ghoſt are compared unto <hi>four great Beaſts,</hi> Dan. 7. 3. Surely earthly Crowns are but baſe and ſordid to the heavenly.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This expreſſion, <hi>a Crown of life,</hi> is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſhew <hi>that the Crown fades not,</hi> will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be leſs bright for wearing, 'twill never be thrown off, 'tis a <hi>living Crown,</hi> a Crown of immortality.</p>
               <p>In the next place follow the Arguments to prove the Doctrine, that the Saints ſhall be thus Crowned; and they are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. One ſhall be drawn <hi>from the Fathers good pleaſure.</hi> This good pleaſure Chriſt declares to the little flocks encouragement, <hi>Luk. 12. 32. Fear not little Flock, 'tis your
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:60678:72"/> Fathers good pleaſure to give you the Kingdome:</hi> And this his counſel is immutable, he will do this his pleaſure. This pleaſure he hath plainly ſignified in his Covenant and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, wherein <hi>Glory</hi> as well as <hi>Grace</hi> is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured: and hereby he hath heightned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vers hopes and expectations; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to fruſtrate them is not conſiſtent with his truth and goodneſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſecond Argument ſhall be drawn from <hi>Chriſts purchaſe;</hi> He hath <hi>purchaſed that poſſeſſion</hi> for his Saints in the next world; he hath bought that Crown by his Croſs. In the New Teſtament the Lord Jeſus hath bequeathed life to them, and <hi>by the Death of Himſelf the Teſtatour, this Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is confirmed,</hi> Heb. 9. 16. So that this Life is as ſure, as 'tis ſure our Lord dyed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A third Argument ſhall be drawn <hi>from Chriſts entring into life, and taking poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Kingdome.</hi> He liveth, and was dead, and behold he is alive for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vermore: He is ſet down with his Father in his Throne, and is gone thither partly to this end, that he might fit Crowns and prepare Manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for his perſevering followers, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 2.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A fourth Argument ſhall be drawn <hi>from the for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aſts of this glorious life that at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent are vouchſafed.</hi> Life ſpiritual is Life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal in the Bud, and the Bud will at
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:60678:72"/> length be fully blown. In Ordinances an heaven upon earth is ſomtimes enjoyed. Oh then how are the things unſeen made evident! When faith and ſpiritual ſenſe and experience go together, then there is that which the Apoſtle calls <hi>a full aſſurance of underſtanding,</hi> Col. 2. 2.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A fifth Argument ſhall be drawn <hi>from the earneſt of the Spirit,</hi> Eph. 1. 13, 14. <hi>In whom after that ye believed, ye were ſealed with that holy Spirit of promiſe, which is the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of our inheritance until the Redemption of the purchaſed poſſeſſion to the praiſe of his Glory.</hi> And in other places we read of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arneſt of the Spirit.</hi> The Spirit of wiſdome and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation makes the Saints know what is the hope of their Calling, and what the riches of their glorious inheritance. And the Lord gives his Spirit, not only to reveal this to them, but as an earneſt and pledge to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them of it, and that after they are made meet to be partakers of the life and glory which he hath promiſed, they ſhall undoubtedly enjoy it. I come at laſt to the Uſes.</p>
               <div n="1" type="application">
                  <head>USE I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Inſtruction.</hi> We may learn the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul condition of the ungodly: a Crown there is, but not for them; a glorious life above, but they ſhall dye the everlaſting death. By the ungodly I mean they that allow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:60678:73"/> in ſin, which the Word and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience tels them they ought to caſt away. Not only the open unbeliever, but the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret hypocrite is concerned, who is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believer as well as the other. When theſe do read of Heavens joyes, it ſhould fill them with ſorrow to conſider, that their <hi>triumph will be but ſhort, and their joy will laſt but for a moment,</hi> Job 20. 5. There are theſe Five things that will exceedingly aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate the loſs of life to the ungodly.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>This life was proffer'd often to the ungodly in the Goſpel.</hi> The Fountain of living wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters was not a Fountain ſealed, but 'twas ſet open; and yet this Fountain was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken for the ſake of broken Ciſterns. The Spirit and the Bride ſay <hi>come,</hi> the Miniſters of the Goſpel ſay <hi>come,</hi> and the ſinners preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing neceſſity and want ſayes <hi>Go,</hi> and drink of the waters of life, ſince thou mayeſt do it <hi>freely,</hi> Rev. 22. 17. and yet he refuſeth to accept the invitation. Pardon goes as it were a begging, and Glory a begging in the Goſpel, and yet neither are accepted, though offered upon terms moſt juſt and reaſonable. Oh how will it torture the damned to reflect upon this, that <hi>they would not come to Chriſt,</hi> though life was aſſured upon their coming, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 40.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. 'Twill heighten the miſery of undone
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:60678:73"/> ſinners <hi>to conſider what they preferr'd before this Crown of life.</hi> Oh where were their wits, when ſin was cheriſhed in their hearts, while Chriſt ſtood at the door? When the world that is ſo empty, ſo unſtable, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o enſnaring, was lookt upon as a better inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance then that which is incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Some that periſh, have been not far from the kingdom.</hi> The ſpirit of God hath ſtriven; their own ſpirits have been ſtartled, and almoſt perſwaded to turn indeed; and if they had done ſo, they would have <hi>lived,</hi> this crown had been their own: But ſome ſin or other was a cord to hold them faſt; ſome command wherein ſuffering, ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial, ſtrictneſs is enjoyned, made them firſt demur, then conſulting with fleſh and blood, to take offence at Chriſt, and ſo away. And 'tis an hightning of miſery, to have been<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> near to happineſs, &amp; through our own fault and folly to have miſs't of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The ungodly hereafter <hi>will have other apprehenſions of this crown which they have ſlighted.</hi> When they ſee the Prophets, and Apoſtles, and Saints in the Kingdom, and do perceive what a luſtre their crowns have; what bliſs, and glory is their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Oh how will they grow mad
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:60678:74"/> mad at themſelves for grief and vexation, that they were ſo ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tiſhly ignorant, to contemn ſuch a treaſure.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Deſpair of ever gaining that Crown of Life will ſeize upon them.</hi> Now there is hope, but hereafter the door of heaven, and the door of hope too will be ſhut, and never open'd more. No prayers will be heard no tears will move compaſſion. Chriſt the giver of life will ſay, <hi>depart ye curſed:</hi> and the invitation to come to him will be heard no more for ever. How will deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration torture them, when they conſider what they have loſt, and how their loſs is irreparable: Fools they lived, and fools they dyed, and then after-wiſdom cannot at all avail them.</p>
                  <p>Bring theſe things to mind, conſider and ſhew your ſelves men, O ye tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſours. When life and death were ſet before you, why ſhould death as the beſt of the two be choſen?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="application">
                  <head>USE II.</head>
                  <p>Of Examination. It highly concerns all to examine whether they have a right to this Crown of life, or no? Moſt expect it, but moſt will be aſhamed of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded hope and expectation. To help you againſt deceiving your own ſouls in this ſelf-examination, I ſhall deſcribe thoſe
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:60678:74"/> that have a title to this Crown, that are indeed the heirs of life: by theſe enſuing characters.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They who have a right to the Crown of life: <hi>are believers on the Son of God, Joh. 3. ult. He that believeth on the Son of God hath ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life</hi> What is it to believe on Chriſt? <hi>'Tis to recieve him as he is offered in the Goſpel</hi> How is Chriſt offered in the Goſpel? <hi>As a Prince, and as a Savi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ur.</hi> Chriſt cannot be received as a Prince, but the dominion of ſin muſt be pulled down. He cannot be received as a Saviour, but our own righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and ſtrength muſt be look't upon as inſufficient and unavaluable to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He that thus hath accepted the Son, hath life by him, 1 Joh. 5. 11. <hi>This is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> record that God hath given us eternal life an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> this life is in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>his Son,</hi> ſeek it elſewhere, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> you will never find it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They who are heirs to the Crown of life, <hi>are quickned by the Spirit.</hi> 'Tis the Spirit that quickens, Joh. 6. 63. Sometime they were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins; but God who is rich in mercy, for the great love wherewith he loved them, did quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them by the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 4 They are alive to God: his ſpirit dwels in them, they breathe after him, they walk in his wayes; they do his work, they aim at
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:60678:75"/> his glory. And this life ſpiritual is the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of, and preparative to that which is eternal.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They who are heirs to the Crown of life, <hi>diligently hearken to the word of God,</hi> they are willing to be reproved for ſin, to be inſtructed concerning duty; they hear, they keep the word as well as hear it, Prov. 10. 17. <hi>He is in the way of life that keepeth inſtruction.</hi> So Prov. 6. 23. <hi>For the commandment is a Lamp, and the Law is light, and the reproofs of inſtruction is the way of life.</hi> The word of God hath not only a convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and a converting, and an edifying power, put 'twill put the crown at laſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the head of the faithful: therefore the Apoſtle affirms it, <hi>able to give the inheritance,</hi> Act. 20. 32. <hi>And now Brethren I commend you to God, and to the word of his Grace, which is able to build you up, and to give you an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance among all them that are ſanctified.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. They who are Heirs to the Crown of Life, <hi>do mortifie the deeds of the body;</hi> by the Spirits help they do it, <hi>Rom. 8. 13. If ye live after the fleſh, ye ſhall dye; but if ye through the ſpirit do mortifie the deeds of the body, ye ſhall live.</hi> The Heirs of life are weary of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of ſin and death; therefore they cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the fleſh with the affections and luſts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>They mortifie their members on earth, forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:60678:75"/> uncleanneſs, inordinate affection, evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, &amp; covetouſneſs which is idolatry,</hi> Col. 3. 5. Every ſin that they ſee, they look upon with an eye of grief and hatred, and ſtrike at it.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. They who are heirs to the Crown of Life <hi>have their fruit unto holineſs,</hi> Rom. 6. 22. <hi>But now being made free from ſin, and become the ſervants of God, ye have your fruit unto holineſs, and the end everlaſting life. The pure in heart ſhall ſee the Lord,</hi> Mat. 5. 8. his back parts now, his face in glory. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the holy are only fit to behold the Holy One. Art thou an enemy to holineſs? Thou art an enemy to thy own life. The heirs of life underſtand that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove is an holy City; <hi>therefore they apply &amp; plead the promiſe of ſanctification; they cleanſe themſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh &amp; ſpirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 7. 1.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. They who are heirs to the Crown of Life <hi>perſevere to the end;</hi> they are faithful to the death, as the Tex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſpeaks; they hold faſt what they have, that none may take their Crown away; they not only begin, but finiſh their courſe, and keep the faith, and ſo they receive a Crown of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at the hand of the Lord, the righteous Judge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="application">
                  <head>USE III.</head>
                  <p>Suffer I beſeech you a few words of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation,</hi>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:60678:76"/> and I ſhall conclude with them.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Let the ſerious and believing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this Crown of life <hi>enliven and quicken you to every duty.</hi> Art thou hearing for a Crown, and praying for a Crown, and wilt thou hear careleſly, and pray coldly? Doth not ſuch a Kingdom as heaven is, deſerve thou ſhouldſt uſe an holy violence to take it? what, ſlothful and dead when ſuch glory is in view? Oh ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait gate, that when thou ſeekeſt to enter in at Heavens door, and cryeſt <hi>Lord, Lord, open to me,</hi> entrance may not be denyed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let this Crown of life be made uſe of <hi>to ſilence Satan, &amp; to fence thee againſt tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> When the Devil tells thee of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſe and gain and pleaſure, which ſin will afford, reply, <hi>Come O thou lying and deceitful ſpirit, put thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aſe and gain and pleaſure into one Ballance, of the Sanctuary, and I will put the Crown of life and glory into the other, and what is</hi> ſinful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſe to the Saints reſt? or the gain of gold, to the Saints glory? or pleaſures for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to eternal rejoycing? Satan will not know what to ſay to this, but perceiving unlikelyhood of prevailing will flee from you.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Let this crown of Life <hi>looſen your hearts from the world.</hi> Do not defile and load
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:60678:76"/> your ſelves with thick clay, do not ſtick faſt therein, when ſuch glory is ſo certain and near at hand. Be not deſirous of, or content with a portion in this life, ſince you are juſt entring upon a better. Live as ſtrangers and pilgrims on earth, &amp; declare plainly that you ſeek a better country then the world hath any.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Let this crown of Life, <hi>ſteel your hearts againſt ſufferings.</hi> Fear not what enemies can do, ſince the keyes of heaven hang not at their girdle, nor glory is given of their pleaſure. Our Lord <hi>ſet the joy before him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo he endured the croſs and deſpiſed the ſhame,</hi> Heb. 12. 2. and if you imitate him, you ſhall at length ſit down where he is at the right hand of the throne of God.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Let this crown of life, <hi>ſet you above the fear of diſſolution;</hi> it cannot be enjoyed till you are gone from hence, you muſt dye before you can live the life above. Let your death be natural or violent, you muſt not be ſtartled or amazed. The Angels are ready to do their office, to convey you to paradiſe: Chriſts arms are open to receive you, which are a part of his purchaſe, and his redeemed ones. Chriſt underſtands what 'tis to dye, 'tis an unuſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al tryal, which you can have experience of but once; unuſual ſtrength ſhall be
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:60678:77"/> afforded. If death were but lookt upon only as a dark paſſage into the glorious and lightſome inheritance, it would be no longer terrible, but deſireable.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. let this crown of Life, <hi>make you long for your Lords appearing.</hi> Oh cry unto him to remove time and dayes out of the way, and that the wheels of his chariot may make greater haſt. Long for the time when the heavens ſhall break aſunder, and the faireſt of ten thouſand ſhall ſhew his face through the clouds, and ſit upon his great white throne to judge the world in righteouſneſs. When he comes <hi>his reward will be with him,</hi> Rev. 2 2. 12. Never a Saint ſhall be ſeen without a crown at that day. And Oh what a ſpectacle will it be to behold the Head, and all the members together! every one having on a rich and ſparkling diadem! The Saints are deſcribed to be ſuch as <hi>love their Lords appearing.</hi> And there is reaſon they ſhould wiſh for it: <hi>For when Chriſt who is their life ſhall appear, then ſhall they alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with him in glory.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60678:77"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
